My conscience won't let me go shoot my brother
我的良心不允许我为了强大的美国
or some darker people
去对自己的兄弟  或是对
or some poor, hungry people in the mud
一些深肤色的人  或者对一些泥泞中
for big, powerful America, and shoot them for what?
贫穷饥饿的人开枪  射杀他们做什么
They never called me "nigger." They never lynched me.
他们从没喊过我黑鬼  没有用私刑处死我
They didn't put no dogs on me.
他们也没放狗咬过我
They didn't rob me of my nationality.
他们更没有剥夺我的国籍
That's one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind.
这对个人来说是一小步  对人类来说是一大步
When you take 20 million black people
马尔科姆·艾克斯 伊利诺伊州  芝加哥 1962年7月11日
and make them fight all your wars
为你出征所有的战争
and pick all your cotton and you never
还让他们为你摘棉花
give them any real recompense,
汤米·史密斯 墨西哥城奥运会 1968年10月16日
sooner or later their allegiance towards you
迟早  他们对你的拥护
is going to wear thin.
会越来越少
America has declared war on black people.
美国已经对黑人宣战
If the link-up is not made
如果不将发生在越南的事
between what's happening in Vietnam and here,
去你妈的征兵
we may very well face a period
我们可能很快就会面对一段
of full-blown fascism very soon.
法西斯主义全面爆发的时代
I shall not seek and I will not accept
我将不会竞选  或者接受
the nomination of my party for another term as your president.
战争犯
America needs a full-time president
美国需要一位能全身心投入工作的总统
and a full-time Congress.
汽油弹炸伤儿童 南越  浪滂县 1972年6月8日
I shall resign the presidency effective at noon tomorrow.
理查德·米尔豪斯·尼克松总统 白宫 1974年8月9号
In the Civil War, 186,000
南北战争中  18万6千黑人
black men fought in the military service,
加入了军队战斗
and we were promised freedom and we didn't get it.
我们被许诺予自由  但并没有得到
In World War II, 850,000 black men fought,
第二次世界大战中  85万黑人参军作战
and we were promised freedom, and we didn't get it.
我们被许诺予自由  也没有得到
Now here we go with the damn Vietnam War,
现在我们又加入了他妈的越南战争
and we still ain't gettin' nothin'
但除了种族歧视的警察暴力执法  和其他歧视
but racist police brutality, et cetera.
我们仍然没有得到任何报偿
God damn!
我靠
My man!
兄弟
- What's going on, man? - How you doing, man?
-你好啊兄弟  -兄弟你怎么样
Oh, my goodness. So good to see you.
我的老天  见到你真是太好了
- You, too, Blood! - Look at you!
-我也是  手足  -瞧瞧你
God damn, Eddie, you still pigeon-toed?
翻译     马丁马丁回音山  布塔 不见
You didn't get that shit fixed?
还没把那毛病治好吗
Well, I decided not to. Why, brother?
我决定不治了  干嘛要治呢  兄弟
The women love it.
女人们都喜欢我这样
Besides, did you know that Jackie Robinson, John Elway,
还有  你知道吗  杰基·罗宾森  约翰·埃尔维
Agassi, Messi, Neymar, Mookie
阿格西  梅西  内马尔  穆奇
and MJ are all pigeon-toed?
还有乔丹都是内八字
And you, shit. Let me give you some power.
还有你也是呢  咱们来碰个拳
- Let me see if I can remember this. - Come on, you got it.
-我看看还记不记得  -来吧  你没问题的
- Okay, all right. Here we go. - Give me some of that black shit.
-好的  就这样  -来点黑人的样子
Get in here. Finally!
拥抱一下  好久不见
Finally!
好久不见
Yeah, man. Look at you.
是啊兄弟  瞧瞧你
- How you doing? - I'm all right. I'm all right.
-你还好吗  -还不错  还不错
Bring it here! There he is.
来吧  看这是谁来了
How we feelin'?
还好吗伙计
Hold on. Finally. Finally.
好了  真是太久没见了
Now, look at you.
瞧你这家伙
- It sure is good to see y'all. - Ain't this some shit?
-能见到你们真是太好了  -真是难得
I'm tellin', it's a stone cold trip being back here in country.
要我说  回到这里我还真是五味杂陈
Baby, we got off that plane,
老天  我们一下飞机
that heat hit me upside the head, ski-bop!
一股热浪就冲上头  轰地一下
Just like in '68.
就像重回了68年
- Yeah, brother man, we are back. - The Bloods is back.
-没错  兄弟们  我们回来了  -誓血队回来了
- 5 Bloods don't die, we just multiply! - Yeah, yeah!
-誓血五人组不会消亡  我们生生不息  -没错
Soon to be five.
马上就会凑齐五人了
- Amen. - Amen.
-阿门  -阿门
Look what I found.
看看我找到了什么
Young Blood.
年轻的手足
- Get you home, Blood. - Damn.
-我们带你回家  兄弟  -靠
Brother man in all his glory.
兄弟那时候真是年轻气盛
- Amen. - Let me see it, man.
-阿门  -我瞧瞧
- Uh, ma'am? - Yes, sir.
-女士  -什么事  先生
Can you please make sure that all four rooms are on my card?
请你把四个房间的费用都刷在我的卡上
No, no, thank you. I'm good. I'm good.
不  不  谢了  不用了
- Hey, on me, remember? - Nah, nah, I got mine.
-说好我付的  记得吗  -不用了  我自己付
I ain't your welfare charity case.
我不需要你做慈善
Ain't nobody saying no shit like that.
你们别说这种胡话
Everybody know your black ass and that big black Amex card,
大家都知道你牛逼  拿着张运通黑卡
the biggest fucking car dealership in the world, right?
开着他妈全世界最大的车行  行了吧
Keep your money, man.
不用你破费了  兄弟
I see your head still hard as hell.
你还是倔强如铁
Just like my Swanson Johnson.
我的老二也一样铁
Man, you crazy as hell, bruh.
兄弟  你可真是够疯的
Hey, y'all know I got an 18-year-old son?
你们知道我有个十八岁的儿子吧
What, he's 18 now?
什么  他都十八岁了
Yeah, check this out.
是啊  看看他
Look at that handsome dude, man.
看这小伙子真帅
Yeah.
没错
Must take after his mama.
肯定是遗传他妈妈的
I got thug-ass hardheads moving into my hood.
我们家附近来了一帮混蛋小混混
Now Cissy wants to move out.
西西现在想搬出去了
You got a piece for protection?
你弄了防身武器没有
Yeah, I got a piece for protection. Got a side piece.
是的  弄了枪防身  还养了情人
I got Smith on one side and c on the other.
一个叫史密斯小姐  一个叫威森小姐
- Money, please. - No. You gotta go. You gotta go, son.
-请给点钱  -不  走开  走吧孩子
I'm good. Man.
真烦人  靠
- GI, GI. - They don't have no age limit in a bar in Vietnam.
-美国兵  美国兵  -越南的酒吧没有年龄限制
No, no, you gotta... Come on, get him the fuck out of here.
不不  你走开...快他妈把他赶走
Money, money. GI.
给点钱  给点钱  美国兵
- There you go, all right. - Twenty bucks.
-给你  行了吧  -二十美元呢
Go.
走吧
Now he got more in his damn cup than I got in my wallet.
现在他杯子里的钱比我钱包里还多
- Man, they'll take you. - Shit.
-简直是打劫  -靠
It's a damn shame.
太他妈遗憾了
On the real, man.
说真的  兄弟
We got back from Nam, we didn't get nothing but a hard damn time.
我们从越战回去之后可真是不好过
- Folks called us baby killers. - Yeah.
-被人们称为孩子杀手  -是啊
See, I bought into all that bullshit.
我完全信了那一套说法
How did your life change? Yeah, right.
你的生命发生了什么变化吗  完全没有
Time we got these free-loading immigrants
是时候把那些吃白食的移民赶走
off our backs and build that wall.
建一堵墙不让他们进来
Negroes better wake the fuck up with the quickness, man.
黑鬼们真应该快点觉醒
- No, no, no, no, no! - I'm just saying. I'm--
-不不  不是吧  -我就随口一说
Don't tell me that you voted for President Fake Bone Spurs.
你不会给伪造骨刺总统投票了吧
- Yeah, I voted for him. - Get the fuck out of here.
-是的  我投票给他了  -少他妈扯了
He didn't vote for him.
他才没投给他
- I thought that was you. - Impeach him.
-我就知道那个人是你  -弹劾他
That grinnin'-ass Negro on the front row.
那个站在前排欢欣雀跃的黑鬼
Right there behind Trump at that rally.
那次竞选拉票就站在特朗普身后
"Ha! Ha! It's me! It's me!"
"看啊  看啊  是我  是我"
Blacks for Trump, you watch.
黑人支持特朗普当选  瞧好了
You watch. Those signs are great, thank you.
瞧好了  那些标语太棒了  谢谢
Fake news.
假新闻
See? That's what they all go to.
你看  他们都那么说
- Fake news. - Always go to that one.
-说是假新闻  -都用假新闻开脱
Yeah. I'm tired of not getting mine, man.
我真是受够了得不到任何报偿  兄弟
I feel you. I feel you.
我懂你  我懂你
Been fucked my whole goddamn life, bruh. Goin' for me!
一辈子都被压榨  什么时候好事轮到我
- Shit. - For real.
-靠  -说的没错
I mean, back in the day,
想当年
- being a brother meant something. - Yeah, man.
-兄弟情谊是有意义的  -没错  兄弟
We fought against the man.
我们共同对抗恶人
- We loved one another. - Amen.
-我们互相关爱  -阿门
We became ace boon coon blood brothers
我们在那个该死的丛林里
out there in that damn jungle.
成为了情同手足的誓血兄弟
- Preach on it. - Yeah.
-说得太对了  -没错
- Stormin' Norm demanded it. - He did.
-暴风诺曼的命令  -没错
- Sure did. - All right, come on.
-没错  -来吧兄弟们
Yeah. Here we go. Boom!
走一个  碰
Boom! All right, yeah.
碰  好样的
- Otis. - Vinh.
-奥蒂斯  -温
- This is our guide, Vinh. - Hey, I'm Eddie.
-这是我们的向导  温  -你好  我是埃迪
- Vinh. - I'm Melvin, man.
-我是温  -我是梅尔文
- Nice to meet you. - How you doing?
-很高兴认识你  -你好
- Good. - Paul, man.
-挺好  -我是保罗
- Good to meet you. - Yeah.
-很高兴认识你  -一样
Gentlemen, welcome back to Vietnam.
先生们  欢迎你们回到越南
- Thank you. - Thank you, man.
-谢谢  -谢了  伙计
- I have itinerary for you. - That's for you.
-这是你们的行程  -给你
- For you. - Thank you.
-给你  -谢谢
- For you. - Pull up a seat.
-给你  -坐吧
I still think hiking into the jungle
我仍然认为徒步进入丛林
without me as your guide is a big mistake.
不带着我作为向导是个很大的错误
- We know that jungle, man. - Yes, we sure do.
-我们熟悉那片丛林  兄弟  -没错  很了解
Oh, yeah.
确实
Do you have the necessary documents?
你们有必需的文件吗
Yes, there you go.
有的  给你
From the Pentagon... and from the Vietnamese government.
五角大楼的  越南政府的
When we locate Norman's remains,
等我们找到诺曼的遗骸
the DPAA is gonna send in a recovery team
美国国防部战俘及失踪军人统计署
to bring him back home.
会派人来把他带回国
Arlington National Cemetery.
他要葬在阿灵顿国家公墓
Hey, man, what the... what the fuck are they staring at, man?
我说  他们他妈的  他妈的在看什么呢
Who?
谁
Those two right there.
那边那两个家伙
Shit. Those two over there,
靠  那边那两个家伙
they've been staring at us for the last ten minutes.
他们盯着我们看了十分钟了
- Just chill, man. Just chill. - Chill? People staring at me, man.
-放松  兄弟  冷静  -放松  有人盯着我呢
Staring at all of us.
盯着我们所有人
Those gentlemen just buy you this drink.
这些酒是那两位先生请你们的
They are former Viet Cong
他们是老越共
and wanna welcome you all back to their country.
欢迎你们回到他们的国家
Yeah?
是吗
- One of them is my cousin, Nguyen. - Get outta here.
-其中一位是我表亲  阮  -得了吧
And my father's younger brother.
另一位是我父亲的弟弟
- But you're from the south. - They fought for the north.
-但你是南越人  -他们当时是为北越而战的
Nguyen does tours for North Vietnamese tourists.
阮给北越游客当导游
The American War turned Vietnamese family
美国发动的越南战争让越南人
against Vietnamese family.
自己人跟自己人反目
- Paul. - Hey, man.
-保罗  -我说
Those could've been the dudes
搞不好就是他们
that zapped Norm, that's all I'm saying.
杀了诺姆  我就想说这点
Will you raise your goddamn glass?
你赶紧把杯子举起来行吗
The American War is over. Come on.
越南战争已经结束了  赶紧的
Come on, man.
来吧  伙计
Good night.
晚安
- Feelin' the love. - Look at him.
-感觉到爱了  -瞧瞧他
- I tell ya. - I know.
-说真的  -我懂
GI! GI!
美国兵  美国兵
Now I know why this mission was so damn important.
现在我明白这任务为什么这么重要了
It's about what this war is all about.
这关乎这场战争的本质
There it is.
没错
All right, Bloods. Our objective is in the C-47.
好了  誓血队  咱们的目标在那架C-47上
Hold yourself! Hold on!
都抓紧了  抓牢
- Come on. - Hold on!
-挺住啊  -抓稳
- Lock it up! - Cover the Bloods to the plane!
-火力封锁  -掩护誓血队去飞机那边
- Go! Go, man! You got it! - Harlow and Cots, KIA!
-快走  可以的  -哈罗和科兹阵亡
Lay down cover fire!
趴下  火力掩护
Go!
上
Reloading.
正在装弹
- Reload! - Reloading.
-装弹  -正在装弹
Move out! Move out!
出去  快出去
Fuck! Jammed!
该死  卡住了
Come on! Go!
快点  上
Move, move, move!
跑起来  快  快
Go, go, go!
上上上
Go!
上
Man down! Man down!
有人中弹  有人中弹
Check fire. Paul! Get up! Get up!
暂停开火  保罗  快起来  起来
Team one, take security!
第一小队  注意防守
Set security!
布防
Hey, Paul, come inside!
保罗  快进来
Clear!
安全
Bloods!
誓血队
Yo, come on in here.
大伙都进来
All right. Let's see what we got here.
好了  来看看这都有什么
- Out of sight! - Great googly-moogly.
-闪瞎我了  -妈妈咪呀
You know what this means?
知道这意味着什么吗
We gold standard.
我们有黄金兜底了
I've run many tours for GIs from the American War.
我给很多越南战争中的美国兵当过导游
Glad you can now see our country in a different light.
很高兴你们现在能看到我们国家的另一番景象
Will you look at this?
瞧瞧啊
- It's a whole different place. - I can't believe it.
-这完全变了个地方  -真不敢相信
They didn't need us. They should've just sent Mickey D's,
其实根本用不着我们  他们当初只要把麦当劳
Pizza Hut and The Colonel,
必胜客和肯德基派过来
and we would have defeated the V.C. in one week.
只要一周就能打败越共了
- You got it. - Finger-lickin' good.
-这个梗好  -吮指原味棒
Paul, when did you serve?
保罗  你服役是哪几年
I did three tours, man. '67 to '71.
我派驻过三次  67年到71年
1st Infantry.
第一步兵团的
Were you involved in Operation Junction City?
你参与过章克申城的行动吗
We were there. We were all there.
在  我们当时都在
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
对  没错
My father was there, too.
我父亲当时也在
- Yeah? - 25th Infantry, ARVN.
-是吗  -南越共和军  25步兵团的
He fought to the very last man.
他奋战到了最后
My brother, give it to me. Give it to me.
好兄弟  来一个  来
My family was here in Saigon when it fell.
西贡沦陷时  被我们一家赶上了
My dad spent 18 months in a communist re-education camp.
我爸在一个共产党劳改营里待了一年半
Many other were not so lucky.
其他很多人就没那么幸运了
Hey, y'all remember those fugazi Rambo movies?
你们还记得那些蒙人的《第一滴血》系列电影吧
- Sly. - Yeah.
-史泰龙演的  -对
I like them shits, man.
我还挺喜欢的
You gotta be fucking kidding me, man.
你在逗我吧  哥们
Him and that... that dude, uh, Walker, Texas Ranger.
他和那个叫啥来着  沃克  《德州骑警》
- I ain't saying nothing about him. - Man!
-我可没说喜欢他  -拜托
Out there trying to save some imaginary POWs.
到处瞎跑想拯救臆想出来的战俘
All them Holly-weird motherfuckers
就是好莱坞那帮混蛋怪胎
trying to go back and win the Vietnam War.
想回去打赢越战
Yeah. I would be the first cat in line
是啊  如果有电影能讲述正真的英雄
if there was a flick about a real hero,
我愿意第一个排队买票
you know, one of our blood. Somebody like Milton Olive.
讲述我们的兄弟  像米尔顿·奥利弗那样的人
That man jumped on that grenade and saved his Bloods' lives.
那哥们舍身护住手榴弹  救了他兄弟们的命
And he was the first brother
他是第一个在越南
to be awarded the Medal of Honor in Nam.
被授予荣誉勋章的黑人兄弟
Eighteen years old.
才十八岁
Look, I love y'all and all that bullshit,
我爱你们还有那些废话
but, uh, I ain't doin' that.
但我可不会去挡手榴弹
Man, nobody want you to die for them.
没人希望你为他们送命
'Cause I ain't.
我不会的
Like Aretha sang, "You better think."
就像阿雷莎唱的那样  "你最好想清楚"
- Oh, Vinh. - What the fuck he talkin' about?
-温  -他说什么呢
Listen, Bloods, I'm out, all right? Thank you very much.
誓血队  我该走了  好吗  非常感谢
- Thank you. - All right.
-谢谢  -好吧
Be careful, man.
小心点  伙计
I'll be careful. Later.
我会小心的  回见
Where's he going?
他要去哪
He got something to take care of, man.
他有点事要处理
Tien...
田...
you have hardly changed.
你几乎没变
We both know that's not true.
咱俩都知道这是客套话
But thank you for being so kind.
但还是谢谢你的好意
You look like you've done well for yourself.
看来你过得不错啊
We find a way.
我们总得找到安身之道
- Yes, we do. When we can. - Yes.
-是啊  只要还有能力  -是的
The gold is belong to Vietnamese government.
金子现在归越南政府所有了
Monsieur Desroche converts the gold into cash.
德罗什先生能把金子变现
He's the only person that I know
我认识的人里只有他
who can handle a transaction of this size.
能处理这么大额的兑换
- Have you dealt with him before? - Yes.
-你以前跟他打过交道吗  -是的
He's expensive. 20%.
他很贵  要抽两成
And I will need 10%.
我还要一成
And there's no other way to move this?
没有其他办法转移了吗
International export is my business.
我就是做国际出口生意的
- It's why you call me. - Yeah.
-你也是为此才找的我  -对
This is my daughter, Michon.
这是我女儿  米雪
And this is my old friend Otis. From American War.
这是我的老朋友奥蒂斯  他参加过越南战争
- It's, uh... - Hello, Otis.
-非常...  -你好  奥蒂斯
It's very nice to meet you.
非常高兴见到你
Thanks, my dear.
谢谢  亲爱的
Is, uh...
她...
Is, uh... Is that our daughter? Our...
她是我们的女儿吗  我们的...
Yes, she is.
是的
She was a bastard child of the enemy.
当年在人们眼中  她是敌军的野种
I was a whore.
而我是妓女
Her father was a moi, the nigger.
她父亲是个黑鬼
The white GI taught us that word.
白人美国兵教给我们的这个词
Everyone want us out.
人人都想赶我们走
We was too dirty to even clean the toilet.
我们太肮脏  连打扫厕所都不配
They call our beautiful Michon the cockroach.
他们管我们美丽的米雪叫蟑螂
No.
不了
Good night, Tien.
晚安  田
Good night, Otis.
晚安  奥蒂斯
May I ask, how did they end up in your possession?
我能问问吗  你们是怎么弄到这些的
You ask a lotta goddamn questions, wringer.
你问题还真多啊  绞肉机
Monsieur, maybe they're from a bank
先生  这有可能是
you just knocked off in Manila.
你们刚从马尼拉的银行里抢的
Or maybe the authorities are looking for them.
也可能政府也正在找它们
I don't need that kind of shit.
我可不想惹那种麻烦
We ain't no international criminals, you dig?
我们不是国际罪犯  好吗
In my line of work, I have to be very careful,
干我们这行的  得万分小心
and that means knowing exactly who I am in business with.
这就意味着得了解清楚打交道的对象
This cat getting on my last goddamn nerve, man.
这货快踩到我的底线了  兄弟
Gentlemen, I believe our business is finished.
先生们  我们没什么好谈的了
Hey, wait a minute.
等等
Do me a favor. Sit down, please? Just give us that respect.
帮我个忙  先坐下好吗  给我们点尊重
Where were Frenchies in World War II?
二战的时候法国人在哪
Hitler had y'all by the snails.
希特勒把你们打得屁滚尿流
The goddamn US of A saved your asses.
是美利坚救了你们
If it wasn't for good ol' Uncle Sam, all of yous,
要不是好心的美国政府  你们所有人
y'all be speaking the deutsche eating bratwurst,
今天就该说着德语  吃着腊肠
schnitzels and sauerkraut
炸肉排和泡菜了
instead of croissants, snails and escargot.
而不是牛角面包和法式蜗牛
Come on, Blood. Let it go.
别这样  手足  算了
- No, man, no. - Just let it go!
-不  不行  -算了
No, fuck that. I ain't done.
不  去他的  我还没说完
This motherfucker can't tell me shit.
轮不到这混蛋对我品头论足
My daddy, God rest his soul,
我爸  愿他安息
landed in Normandy and killed beaucoup goose-stepping Nazis.
他登陆了诺曼底  杀了一大堆纳粹
Let me tell you something,
我告诉你
them Nazis weren't no punks neither. Not like you.
那些纳粹也不是吃素的  不像你
- Yeah, okay, I'm done. - You feel better?
-行吧  我说完了  -感觉好点了吗
Yeah.
嗯
I thank you for this ignorant
感谢你这番美国单一视角的
American one-sided version of World War II.
无知的二战言论
Please understand. He taking big risk.
请理解一下  他冒了很大的风险
And we ain't?
我们就没风险吗
DaRoach, we gotta trust you, and you gotta trust us.
大落屎  我们得互相信任
Mr. Desroche...
德罗什先生
Our platoon was ordered to find a C-47 CIA plane
我们排当年奉命搜寻一架坠毁的中情局的C-47
that went down with a payroll for the native people. The Lahu.
上面载着给当地拉祜族人的报酬
Now, they didn't wanna be paid in paper currency,
当时他们不想接收纸币
so Uncle Sam was paying them
所以美国政府用了金条
in gold bars for their help against the V.C.
来报答他们在对付越共时提供的帮助
Well, we found the gold, and we...
我们找到了金子  然后...
We bury it. For now. They ask, we say the V.C. Got it.
我们先埋起来  他们问起就说被越共抢了
Later on, we come back and collect.
晚点我们再回来拿
You mean rip it off.
你是说我们私吞了
We ain't ripping off shit!
我们什么也没私吞
Who feel like they're ripping something off?
谁觉得自己是在私吞东西
We was the very first people
我们黑人是第一批
that died for this red, white and blue.
拿命保卫这红白蓝旗的人
Yeah, that's right.
这是事实
It was a soul brother,
那可是一条命  兄弟
Crispus Attucks at the motherfuckin' Boston Massacre.
波士顿惨案中的克里普斯·阿塔克斯
We been dying for this country from the very get,
我们从一开始就在为这个国家牺牲
hoping one day they'd give us our rightful place.
希望有一天他们会给我们应有的地位
All they give us was a foot up our black asses. Well, fuck that.
结果他们根本不把我们黑人当回事  操
I say the USA owe us. We built this bitch!
美国欠我们的  这国家是我们建造的
So, what you sayin', Blood?
你想说什么  手足
I'm saying... we repossess this gold...
我想说的是  我们收回这批金子
like they about to come
就像他们要来
repossess your cash yield convertible now.
收回你们可兑换的现金收益
We repossess this gold for
为了每一个牺牲在战场黑人
every single black boot that never made it home.
我们收回这些金子
Every brother and sister
为了1619年
stolen from Mother Africa to Jamestown, Virginia
从非洲被人贩卖到弗吉尼亚州詹姆斯镇的
way back in 1619.
每一个兄弟姐妹
We give this gold to our people.
我们把这批金子给我们的同胞
You feel that? You feel it?
明白吗  明白吗
- Now, let's bury our gold. - Reparations.
-把我们的金子埋起来吧  -这是补偿
Bloods.
誓血队
We went back a few weeks later, but the area was napalmed,
几周后我们回去  但那里已经被轰炸过了
and we lost all of our landmarks.
所有的标记都没了
But recently, a mudslide
但是最近因为一场泥石流
has exposed what might be the C-47's tail,
C47运输机的尾部可能露出来了
and satellite pictures have pinpointed the spot.
卫星图片已经确定了位置
You're more informed than your friend here.
你比你朋友懂得多
Sir, are you in or out?
先生  你到底加不加入
This is my last offer per kilo,
这是每公斤的最终报价
less my commission.
不包括我的佣金
Tien said 20.
田说了两成
One cannot carry millions of dollars through US Customs.
你们是无法携带数百万美元通过美国海关的
The extra two points will get you a dummy corporation
另外的2%可以给你们注册一个挂名公司
and a tax-free offshore account in Macau.
以及一个在澳门的免税海外账户
You can then withdraw the funds from any bank in the world.
然后你们就能在世界上任何一家银行提取资金
How do I know that you two ain't a con artist team?
我怎么知道你们俩不是骗子团伙的人
As you said, you simply must trust us.
正如你所说  你必须相信我们
Yeah, well, the extra 2% comes outta her cut.
从她的抽成里分出额外的2%
That's right.
没错
- I'll cover it. - Price of doing business.
-算我的  -做生意就要付出代价
- So, we good? - Yeah.
-同意吗  -好
- I'm good. - Yeah, I'm good.
-同意  -同意
And, sir,
先生
Uncle Sam did no better than France in Vietnam.
美国政府和法国一样在越南都没做好事
Gentlemen, I look forward to seeing you again in a few days.
先生们  期待几天后再见到你们
If you will excuse me,
失陪了
I have a lot of things to do for all of us.
我有很多事要为大家做
And...
还有
vive la France.
法兰西万岁
This motherfucker, man.
这个混蛋
I don't take that.
我不相信
What the fuck are you doing here?
你来干什么
I'm worried about you.
我担心你
Why?
为什么
- Well, I found out you were coming here. - And?
-我发现你要来这里  -然后呢
And I came to check on you.
我来看看你
You don't give a flying fuck about me.
你他妈根本不在乎我
I do. You been acting more crazy than usual.
我在乎  你比平时还要疯
Yeah, well...
好吧
you consider me checked on.
现在你看完了
You're here for the gold.
你是来找金子的
Don't lie.
别骗我
You're going after the gold. I read Otis' emails.
你是来找金子的  我看了奥蒂斯的邮件
You gotta choose better passwords. "1-2-3-4"?
你得设个好点的密码  "1234"
Come on now, Dad.
爸  你不是吧
What do you want, David?
你想怎么样  大卫
- An equal share for helping you find it. - Hell to the naw!
-我帮你们找金子  你们跟我平分  -滚蛋
The authorities find out about this,
如果当局发现这件事
y'all go back to the crib empty-handed.
你们就要空手而回了
So, you just a lil' jive-ass gangster now?
你现在变成满口胡话的流氓了吗
After everything you've put me through,
你让我受了那么多罪
I'd say you getting a basement bargain.
我觉得这样已经很便宜你了
You ungrateful lil'...
你个忘恩负义的
lil' Black Studies teacher nigga.
教黑人研究的黑鬼
You want to tell your Bloods or should I?
是你自己告诉誓血队  还是我去说
You sure know how to raise 'em, don't you?
你可真是养了个好儿子
What happens if we bum-rush your boy
如果我们把你儿子赶出去
and throw his ass off that balcony?
把他从阳台上扔下去呢
Know I'm taking a couple of you OGs with me.
我会拉你们几个老混蛋一起垫背的
- Don't ever threaten my son, man. - Or what?
-别威胁我儿子  -不然怎样
Or you will nab more trouble than you know what to do with.
不然我让你更加吃不了兜着走
- Come on! - Come on!
-你少来  -你才少来
Cool it, God damn it! Cool it!
冷静点  该死的  冷静点
David, you are not getting a full share.
大卫  我们不会和你平分的
- You and your daddy can split a share. - You can forget that.
-你和你爸分一份  -想得美
You take it or leave it.
爱要不要
You see what you made me do, man?
看到你把我逼成什么样了
Let me tell you somethin'.
我告诉你
You ain't been nothin' but an anchor around my neck
从你出生的那天起
since the day you were born.
你就是个累赘
Yeah, I said it, and I mean it, too. Take this shit.
我说出来了  我是认真的  拿着
God damn it.
该死的
David, you're a buck private in this outfit.
大卫  在这里你就是个小兵
You do what we say when we say it.
我们叫你做什么  你就做什么
No questions asked. Understood?
不准质疑  清楚了吗
Overstood, Godfather.
再清楚不过了  教父
I have bad feeling about this, Otis.
我对这事有不好的预感  奥蒂斯
I'm gonna be all right.
我不会有事的
Gold does strange things to people.
金子会对人产生奇怪的影响
Even old friends. Be safe.
即使是老朋友  小心点
All right. Yeah.
好吧
I just hope I don't have to use it.
我只是希望我不必用这个
I'll see you in a bit, all right?
回头见
- You just gonna stay there? - Motherfucker, go around.
-你不打算挪一下吗  -混蛋  绕过去
- David. - Yeah?
-大卫  -嗯
Why did you come here?
你为什么来这里
Well, he's my dad.
他是我爸
Feels like my last chance with him.
这是我和他修复关系的最后机会
- He needs counseling. - I know.
-他需要心理治疗  -我知道
Talks to himself.
他自言自语
Your pops was never the same after we lost Norman.
诺曼死后  你老爸就不一样了
- You know, he calls his name in his sleep. - I can believe that.
-他做梦也叫他的名字  -这点我相信
- Who was that guy? - Norm?
-他是什么人  -诺姆吗
That brother was the best damn soldier that ever lived.
那兄弟是有史以来最优秀的士兵
Wasn't many brothers who made squad leader.
能当上班长的兄弟不多
The man was using Bloods for cannon fodder.
政府用黑人做炮灰
White boys who stayed in college, they'd dodge that shit.
大学里出来的白人男孩  他们不会上阵杀敌
They put our poor black asses on the front line,
他们让我们这些可怜的黑人上前线
killing us off like flies.
害我们死伤无数
Stormin' earned his name, was in all kind of firefights.
暴风的名号实至名归  他参与了各种枪战
Trained us in the way of the jungle.
训练我们在丛林中作战
Made us believe that we would get home, alive.
让我们相信我们会活着回家
To your left!
去左边
- To your left! - To the left! Go, go!
-去左边  -去左边  上
Go!
上
- Cease fire! - Cease fire!
-停火  -停火
- Everybody all right? - Yeah.
-大家都没事吧  -没事
- Good right here. - Good, good.
-没事  -没事
War is about money.
战争是为了钱
Money is about war.
钱是为了战争
Every time I walk out my front door,
每次我走出门
I see cops patrolling my neighborhood
我看到警察在我家附近巡逻
like it's some police state.
就像是极权国家
I can feel just how much I ain't worth.
我能感觉到自己有多么一文不值
Gave us something to believe in.
他给了我们信仰
A direction, a purpose.
一个方向  一个目标
He taught us about black history
他教我们那些年
when it wasn't really popular back then.
还不太流行的黑人历史
Schooled us about drinking
教我们不要相信
that anti-commie Kool-Aid they was selling.
政府宣传的那套反共狗屁
Yeah, he was our Malcolm and our Martin.
马尔科姆·艾克斯  美国北部黑人领袖 马丁·路德·金  美国黑人民权运动领袖
Norm had a way of keeping us from going off.
诺姆有办法让我们不要误入歧途
He wasn't no Tom.
他跟政府不同
He was a bad mother, shut your mouth.
他心狠手辣  让你不敢有怨言
Like Ali.
就像拳击手阿里
This is the voice of Vietnam,
这里是越南之音
broadcasting from Hanoi,
越南民主共和国首都
capital of the Democratic Republic of Vietnam.
河内广播电台
Black GI,
黑人美国兵
in Memphis, Tennessee,
在田纳西州孟斐斯
a white man assassinate Dr. Martin Luther King...
一名白人暗杀了马丁·路德·金博士
who heroically opposed the cruel
那位英勇反对
racial discrimination in the USA.
美国残酷种族歧视的人
Dr. King also opposed the US war in Vietnam.
金博士也反对美国在越南的战争
Black GI,
黑人美国兵
your government sent 600,000 troops
你们的政府派遣了六十万人的部队
to crush the rebellion.
田纳西州  孟斐斯
Your soul sister and soul brothers
你们的黑人兄弟姐妹
are enraged in over 122 cities.
加利福尼亚州  奥克兰
They kill them while you fight against us,
你们跟我们打仗的时候  他们都被杀害了
so far away from where you are needed.
他们需要你们  你们却远在天边
Black GI, the South Vietnamese people are resolute
伊利诺斯州  芝加哥
against these fascist acts against Negroes
法西斯对争取民权
who struggle for civil rights and freedom.
和自由的黑人的暴行
Negroes are only 11% of the US population,
黑人只占美国人口的11%
but among troops here in Vietnam, you are 32%.
但在越南的军队中  你们却占到32%
Black GI, is it fair to serve more than the white Americans
美国黑人兵  比派你们来这里的白人服役更多
that sent you here?
这样公平吗
Nothing is more confuse than to be ordered into a war to die
奉命参加一场战胜而牺牲或终身残废
or to be maimed for life
却对正在发生的事情一无所知
without the faintest idea of what's going on.
是最让人疑惑不解的
I dedicate this next record
我把下一张唱片
to the soul brothers of the 1st Infantry Divisions.
献给第一步兵师的黑人兄弟们
Big Red One, 2nd Battalion, 136th Regiment.
大红一师136团第二营
Have a good day, gentlemen.
祝各位度过愉快的一天
Be safe.
保重
- Goddamn bullshit. - Got the wrong motherfucking enemy!
-太他妈扯了  -搞错敌人了
Yeah, goddamn white man gone too far.
对  该死的白人太过分了
- The Bible says an eye for an eye. - And a tooth for a tooth.
-《圣经》说以眼还眼  -以牙还牙
We need to kill some crackers.
我们得去杀点白人
Our brothers and sisters are burnin' shit down back home, Norm.
我们的兄弟姐妹都在老家奋起反抗  诺姆
I love you, man, but you're wrong. Dead wrong.
我爱你  但是你错了  大错特错
You're talking about Dr. King.
你们说的是金博士
You're talking about a man of peace.
你们说的是一个热爱和平的人
And that's what got Dr. King killed.
那就是金博士被人暗杀的原因
I'm as mad as everybody.
我和大家一样愤怒
All us Bloods got a right to be, but...
我们都有权愤怒  但是
we Bloods.
我们誓血队
Won't let nobody use our rage against us. We control our rage.
不会让别人利用我们的愤怒  我们要控制愤怒
Now, what y'all are trying to do right now ain't changing shit.
你们现在想做的事不会改变什么
So, stand down. That's an order.
所以别闹了  这是命令
Nah. Fuck an order, Norm!
不  去你的命令  诺姆
You're gonna have to kill me first.
那你们先杀了我再说
Blood on Blood.
手足相残
And let me tell you, out of all of us,
我这么说吧  在我们之中
your pops was closest to him.
你老爸和他关系最亲近
Believed in Norman like a religion.
像信教一样信赖诺曼
I don't think he believed in anything since.
我看他在那之后再也没信过别的东西
Floating market. You brothers want anything?
水上市场  你们有什么需要吗
Is there some barbecue up in here?
这边有烤肉吗
I might get a couple of things.
我有点想买的东西
What's that? You got bananas?
那是什么  有香蕉吗
Hey, who wants a cold one?
谁想来点冰的
- Six pack. - Bring 'em on up.
-六瓶  -拿过来吧
Hey, don't let her get on.
别让她上来
That's good.
很好
- Oranges? - Get your beer here.
-橙子  -给你的啤酒
This is good.
这个很好
- Here you go. - You're gonna cut it open?
-给你  -你会把它切开吗
No, I'm good. So, how you eat it?
不了  我不用  那怎么吃
It tastes like chicken.
味道像是鸡肉
That probably don't taste like chicken. That's race-related.
估计不像鸡肉吧  这话有种族歧视嫌疑
Got any money?
有钱吗
No, man. Not today. Không.
不  今天算了  不了
Không. Không. No.
先生
Let me get some bananas.
我买点香蕉吧
- I know, that's what I'm getting. - Bananas.
-我知道  我要买的  -香蕉
- That's amazing. - You see this?
-太神奇了  -看到了吗
No, and thank you. Yes, it is.
不了  谢谢  是的
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
是的  是的
There you go.
去吧
That's great. No, thank you. No, thanks.
很好  不了  谢谢  不了  谢谢
- Hello! - What's up with that?
-你好  -怎么回事
No, not today. Not today.
不了  今天不买  今天不买
No, I don't want it. Nah. No, I--
不  我不要  不  我...
- Chicken. - No, man. I...
-鸡  -不了  我...
No, man. I...
不了  我...
Okay, due respect. No.
好吧  无意冒犯  不买
No. Okay, all due respect, no.
不  好吧  无意冒犯  不买
Vinh, talk to your... Talk to this man.
温  和这位...和这位说一下
Come on, no means no in any motherfucking language, right?
拜托  "不"在所有语言里都是拒绝的意思吧
Come on, man. Come talk to him, man.
拜托  和他说一下
No!
不了
Vinh, come talk to him!
温  和他说一下
No, man! Back up, okay.
不买  退后  好吗
Just back up. Back up, please.
退后  请你退后
Shut the fuck up. I don't wanna hear that gook shit.
闭嘴吧  我不想听这个越南佬说话了
You know what?
知道吗
Fuck this place, man.
这地方太恶心了
Backward-ass people.
一群未开化的人
- Hey! Get that fucking thing off of me! - Hey, get him.
-别让这个破东西碰我  -让他走开
- These backward-ass motherfuckers, man. - Yeah. Let's go.
-这些落后的乡巴佬  -好了  走吧
Shit! I don't know what the fuck he got!
操  不知道他有什么毛病
Come on. Come on, man.
好了  好了
- No, motherfucker! - Let's go. Dad, come on.
-不  乡巴佬  -走吧  爸  好了
Man, it's just a goddamn chicken.
只是一只鸡啦
What?
什么
You don't know nothing about me, man! Fuck that!
你对我一无所知  去你妈的
You don't know shit about me!
你对我一无所知
I didn't kill your mother and father! Fuck you!
我才没杀你父母  去你妈的
You don't know me!
走吧  走吧
Let's go. Come on.
走吧  好了
You don't know what the fuck you're talking about!
你不知道你自己在放什么屁
What the fuck you know about me?
你对我了解多少
Paul, relax!
保罗  冷静
Man, nah! He kept coming up on me!
不  他不停地冲我来
- I know. - What the fuck?
-我知道  -什么鬼
What the fuck is going down?
到底怎么回事
I got you. I got you, brother.
我明白  我在呢  兄弟
Stop talking, and fuck you!
闭嘴吧  去你妈的
- Get the boat moving! - Move on, man!
-开船吧  -滚远点
- I got you. - Stop fucking talking!
-有我在呢  -闭嘴吧
- Don't know shit about me. - You killed my father and mother!
-对我一无所知  -你杀了我父母
What are you doing?
你在做什么
He knows what "gook" means, man!
他能听懂"越南佬"
I don't give a fuck about that!
我他妈才不在乎
I don't give two fucks about that. I tried to talk to the man.
我根本就不在乎  我和他说过了
Put the fucking camera down.
把相机放下吧
You're just having a panic attack.
你只是恐慌发作了
This shit happen to you all the time?
你总是这样吗
- Yeah, he has PTSD. - This happen all the time?
-是  他有创伤后应激障碍  -总是这样吗
- He gets triggered. - Come on.
-他被刺激到了  -得了
The guy off with his shit. It be all right.
那人刺激到他了  会没事的
Hey, David. What you know about it, huh?
大卫  你对此了解多少
You don't know nothin' about this.
你对此完全不了解
- I don't have no fucking-- - Nightmares.
-我根本就没有...  -噩梦
You been having nightmares.
你一直在做噩梦
- He does. - I don't have no nightmares.
-没错  -我没做噩梦
- You do. - We all got PTSD.
-你做了  -我们都有创伤后应激障碍
- Come on and tell me. Look. - Just breathe, come on.
-拜托告诉我  听着  -深呼吸  好了
I see...
我看到...
- Come on. - I...
-说吧  -我...
Come on, bud. Come on. There you go. There you go.
说吧  兄弟  说吧  很好  很好
- Come on. - I see ghosts, y'all.
-说吧  -我看到了鬼魂
I see...
我看到了...
ghosts.
鬼魂
Well, it happens to all of us, man!
我们都经历过
- You seen 'em, too? - Yeah.
-你也看到过  -是的
Dead come to you at night?
死人会在晚上来找你
Stormin' Norm comes to me damn near every night.
暴风诺姆几乎每晚都会来找我
Now, he talk to y'all like he talk to me?
他也会像和我说话一样和你们说话吗
- Brother, come on. - I don't think so.
-兄弟  好了  -我看不会
Come on. Come on.
好了  好了
- Take it easy, man. - Go ahead, get it out.
-放松点  -来吧  呼出来
- Yeah. - Get it out. Come on now.
-好  -呼出来  来吧
- Come on, bud. - Think I'm a crazy fuck, don't you?
-来吧  兄弟  -你们是不是觉得我疯了
No!
没有
- Come on, man. - Smart niggas, huh?
-拜托  -你们这些聪明的黑鬼
- It ain't like that. - Man, don't call me that.
-不是那样的  -别那么叫我
That's right. Y'all saditty niggas don't like that word.
没错  你们这些自以为是的黑鬼不喜欢这个词
You know what, man? Nigga. Nigga.
知道吗  黑鬼  黑鬼
Nigga. Nigga. Nigga!
黑鬼  黑鬼  黑鬼
A yellow nigga.
黄皮肤黑鬼
- What? - You feel me?
-什么  -明白了吗
Look, I'm tired of this bullshit! Squash it!
听着  我受够你的屁话了  别扯了
I'm with you. I'm with you.
我懂你  我懂你
Fists up!
碰拳吧
Get in there, David. Get in there. Put your fist up, David.
来吧  大卫  伸手  伸出拳头来  大卫
Come on.
来吧
You, too, Vinh. Go ahead! Fist up, man.
你也是  温  来吧  伸出拳头来
Come on, Paul.
来吧  保罗
- Bloods! - Norm! Norm!
-誓血队  -诺姆  诺姆
Get that out of my face.
别拍我了
And I told him, "Pick your poison,"
我告诉他  "自己点酒"
and he told the waitress to pick the poison.
然后他让服务员来帮他选
- Excuse me. - Sorry.
-借过  -抱歉
- How's it going, boss? - How you doin'?
-你好吗  老大  -你好吗
I'll be better at the bar.
我去了酒吧就会好起来的
Didn't think I'd meet another American here.
没想到我在这里还能见到美国人
But I'm French.
但我是法国人
- Beg your pardon? - I'm French.
-什么  -我是法国人
Sit.
坐吧
You're traveling alone?
你一个人旅行吗
I'm here with a group of Vietnam vets.
我是和一群越战老兵来的
One is my father.
其中有我父亲
Must be something powerful,
一定是件大事吧
coming back after all these years with your father.
这么多年后和你父亲一起回来
- Yeah, it's powerful all right. - Yeah.
-是  是很大的事  -是啊
What is your name?
你叫什么名字
Hedy. Like Hedy Lamarr. No?
赫蒂  和赫蒂·拉玛名字一样  不认识吗
Old time Hollywood star.
以前的好莱坞影星
But, well, my last name is Bouvier, so...
但我姓布维尔
Cool.
挺好
It's cool.
还行吧
- Uh, I'm David. - Ah, David from the Bible.
-我叫大卫  -取自《圣经》的大卫啊
Like David Ruffin from the Temptations.
和"诱惑"乐团的大卫·鲁芬同名
Motown.
汽车城音乐
Yeah, you got it.
是  没错
Is there another place to go at night around here?
这里还有别的地方晚上可以去吗
Have you ever seen so many scooters in your life?
你这辈子见过这么多电瓶车吗
Thank you.
谢谢
So...
那么
what's their story?
他们是什么来头
Well, Simon is my best friend.
西蒙是我最好的朋友
And Seppo and I use each other for sex once in a blue moon.
塞波和我偶尔会上床
What do you, Simon and Sep... Seppo... Seppo... what do you do?
你  西蒙和塞...塞波  是做什么的
We locate old landmines, and detonate bombs, too.
我们搜寻老地雷  也引爆炸弹
- Wow, okay. - "Wow, okay!"
-好吧  -"好吧"
Yeah, that's some gangster shit. For sure!
这工作够硬核  真的
How does one get involved
你是怎么进入
in the landmine disposal business? Pray tell.
地雷处置行业的  务必告诉我
The Bouviers have a history in Vietnam.
布维尔家族在越南很有历史
It's strange how a war never ends for those involved.
战争对于参战的人来说从未结束  很奇怪
See, like, landmines planted years ago...
比如多年前埋下的地雷
and still harvesting death all these years later.
这些年来却还在害人无数
Back to your family history.
继续讲你的家族历史
My family made several fortunes owning a rubber plantation,
我的家族通过橡胶种植园赚了不少钱
and then they bought up much
然后他们又收购了
more of the rice market and made another fortune.
更多水稻  赚了更多钱
See, the white gold.
所谓的白色金子
Wonderful family business.
迷人的家族生意
But one exception,
只除了一点
we exploited the shit out of the Vietnamese people.
就是我们残酷地压榨了越南人民
So, that's the meaning behind the mines.
所以你排雷是为了这个
So, what did the Bouvier family think about what you do?
布维尔家族怎么看待你的工作
What family?
什么布维尔家族
I'm the founder and the director of LAMB,
我是LAMB的创始人与负责人
which I started three years ago.
这是我三年前建立的组织
Lamb?
羔羊
Yeah, LAMB. Love Against Mines and Bombs.
对  LAMB  用爱清除地雷炸弹
No. I must look like some Patty Hearst heiress
我听起来肯定像是那种继承了亿万家产
who's cast herself as a guilt-ridden bourgeoisie cliche.
却要为那套中产阶级陈词滥调伤春悲秋的人
Hey, look, I know all about bourgeoisie cliches.
我对那套中产阶级的陈词滥调可熟悉了
I'm a poverty-stricken fool who loves teaching kids.
我是个喜欢教书的一贫如洗的白痴
However, my guilt trip is a lot less dangerous than yours.
然而我的赎罪之路可比你的安全多了
- Yeah, less dangerous. - Yeah.
-对  安全多了  -是
Unless you count school shootings.
除非你把校园枪击案算上
School shootings. No fun.
校园枪击案  一点也不好玩
You always been the solid one, always.
你一直都很稳健
Got a... wife who loves you. Daughter who loves you.
有爱你的妻子  爱你的女儿
You got a son who loves you enough for two daddies.
你儿子对你的爱是常人的两倍
I couldn't love David...
我没法爱大卫
back.
以前
You got back to the world, you made that transition.
你回到人世间了  完成了转型
Me, I'm all... fucked up inside.
我  我的内心一塌糊涂
I'm broken, man.
我有残缺  兄弟
Broken.
有残缺
Fuck.
操
- Blood, we're all broken. - Not like me, man.
-手足  我们都有残缺  -跟我不同
Norm and I were holding those
诺姆阵亡的时候
gooks back when the man bought it. I see him.
我和他在抵抗越南佬  我看到了
I saw him die, man.
我亲眼看着他死掉
- So what? You're blaming yourself? - You don't even know.
-所以呢  你为此自责吗  -你完全没有概念
Paul, when we get back to the world,
保罗  等我们回去
I'd like you to come with me to a meeting.
我希望你能和我一起参加互助会
I don't do that "Sit in a circle,
我才不要加入那种"大家团团坐
whine about shit" group thing, man.
一起诉苦"的团体
I don't do it. I never have and I never will.
我不加入  以前没有  以后也不会加入
You got to talk to somebody.
你得和别人倾诉
I talk to my brother Stormin' Norman every single night.
我每晚都和我的兄弟暴风诺曼倾诉
- Yeah. - Oh, oh, oh, drink, drink.
-对  -是喝  喝
Simon.
我叫西蒙
- David. - David. Okay. How's it going?
-我叫大卫  -大卫  好  你好吗
I can't call it.
还行吧
Hey, that dude over there by the bar, is he with you?
吧台那个人  是和你一起的吗
- He's getting pretty shit-faced. - Brotherman.
-他喝大了  -我兄弟
It's been an emotional trip.
这次旅行令人百感交集
It appears so.
显然如此
You Americans are just incredibly uninformed.
你们美国人特别闭塞
I guess you're too busy watching reality TV,
我猜你们都忙着看真人秀
or electing a reality TV clown for a president.
或者选一个真人秀丑角当总统
Knew that was coming.
就知道会提这个
Well, on behalf of all the black folks in the USA,
代表美国全体黑人
which are the only group who didn't vote for the motherfucker,
也就是唯一没有给那个混蛋投票的群体
we plead innocent to all charges,
与那个总统办公室里的三K党
claims, accusations, allegations,
有关的一切指控
and associations connected to the Klansman in the Oval Office,
都和我们没有关系
so help me God.
上帝保佑
The Bloods search for the lost treasure of youth
誓血队要去寻找年轻时遗落的财宝
and the remains of the dearly departed Norman Earl Holloway...
以及亲爱的已逝的诺曼·厄尔·霍洛威的遗体
- We're going. - KIA, December 7th, 1971.
-我们要去  -1971年12月7日阵亡
We're here to bring home a fallen brother. A brother!
我们来此是为了带回一个阵亡的兄弟  兄弟
A tomb is sacred, not to be looted by rogues and vandals.
坟墓是神圣的  不该被盗贼匪徒侵扰
There's gold in them hills! Gold, goddamn it, gold!
那山里有金子  金子  该死的  金子
Thanks for getting us this far, Vinh.
谢谢你把我们送到这里  温
My pleasure.
荣幸之至
I gotta tell you, you put on one hell of a tour.
我得告诉你们  你们要进行一次艰辛的旅行
- Sure do. Thanks Vinhi-vin. - You're welcome.
-当然  谢谢  小温  -不客气
Nothing is more precious than
没什么比自由和独立更珍贵
independence and liberty. Said by our uncle.
我们的叔叔是这么说的
- What uncle? - Uncle Ho Chi Minh.
-什么叔叔  -胡志明
Now he's your uncle?
他变成你叔叔了
Actually, he's the father of modern-day Vietnam.
实际上他是现代越南之父
Like your George Washington.
就像你们的乔治·华盛顿
- Oh, my dear misinformed, misguided... - Thank you.
-我亲爱的被误导的  -谢谢
Vietnamese brother.
越南兄弟
Our Uncle George owned 123 slaves.
我们的乔治大叔有123个奴隶
And as they say in our colonists' second language, touche.
以我们殖民者带来的第二语言来说  讲得好
Get your arms out, man. Get your arms out. And back, too.
胳膊张开  兄弟  胳膊张开  还有背
All right, get my arms and my back, man.
好了  给我胳膊和背上喷一喷
- What's up? - Arms and back!
-怎么了  -胳膊和背
There, I got you. I got you.
好  我来喷  我来
Bloods, I can't believe we back up in this bitch.
誓血队  真是难以置信  我们居然又回来了
I'll meet you at this rendezvous location in a few days.
我几天后在这个集合点和你们会和
- All right. - If you're late or early, don't worry.
-好  -你们到早到晚都不用担心
I'll be there.
我会去的
I hope you find your friend.
希望你们找到你们的朋友
Bon voyage.
一路顺风
- Showtime. - Showtime, baby.
-好戏开场  -好戏开场  宝贝
- Bloods. - I'm gonna teach you that.
-誓血队  -我会教你那个的
Y'all ready?
都准备好了吗
- Yeah, let's go. - Yeah.
-好了  我们走  -好了
You got the paperwork?
你拿了文件吗
You can see I got the paperwork with me.
你能看出我随身带着呢
Is that a MAGA hat? God damn!
那帽子上是"让美国再次伟大"吗  见鬼
Straight, straight. I got you.
直走  直走  交给我
What's Happening Brother - Marvin Gaye
What's Happening Brother - Marvin Gaye
♪ Hey baby, what you know good ♪
♪ 宝贝  有什么好消息吗 ♪
♪ I'm just gettin' back, but you knew I would ♪
♪ 我正要回家  但你早知道会如此 ♪
♪ War is hell, when will it end? ♪
♪ 战争如同地狱  不知何时结束 ♪
♪ When will people start getting together again? ♪
♪ 什么时候人们才能再次团结一致 ♪
♪ Are things really gettin' better, like the newspaper said ♪
♪ 报纸上说的是真的吗  情况真的好转了吗 ♪
♪ What else is new my friend, besides what I read ♪
♪ 除了报纸上的事  还有什么新闻吗 ♪
♪ What's happening? brother ♪
♪ 发生了什么事  兄弟 ♪
How you holding up?
你怎么样
Boy, you ask me that every five minutes.
小子  你隔五分钟就问我一次
You know, I did make it through Nam on my own.
我可是独自撑过了越战
Typical tours, too.
还有好几次派驻
Hey! Hey, hold up.
等等
Let Otis catch up.
等等奥蒂斯
Damn, Paul, you can still hump it out on point.
见鬼  保罗  你还是健步如飞
Oh, yeah, baby.
对  宝贝
What happens if somebody get heatstroke
要是有人中暑
or sprain an ankle or something?
或者崴脚了怎么办
Otis is a medic. A good one, too.
奥蒂斯是医疗兵  而且很厉害
Even took a few rounds out of me once.
甚至还给我取出过几颗子弹
From your black monkey ass, as I recall.
我记得是从你的黑屁股里面
What's that?
那是什么
Water.
水
What? I need to take a breathalyzer test?
怎么  要我做酒精测试吗
- Well, what are those? - It's something for my hip.
-那是什么  -我髋关节痛
I know that. But what are they?
我知道  但你吃的是什么药
OxyContin.
奥斯康定
Are you fuckin' kiddin' me?
你跟我开玩笑吗
You think I'm sneakin' a drink,
你以为我偷偷带了酒
and you on that opioid epidemic shit.
结果你自己在服用阿片类药物
- It's prescribed. - Oh, yeah. You writing the prescriptions?
-我有处方  -你自己写的处方吧
No, the VA. Just like everybody else.
不是  退伍局开的  跟大家一样
You best be careful with that shit.
你吃那个最好留神点
- What is this, an intervention? - You need one?
-这是干什么  开劝导大会吗  -你需要吗
Y'all think I'm a junkie?
你们觉得我是个瘾君子
Oh, shit.
见鬼
There. I don't need this shit.
看吧  我不需要这垃圾
This way.
这边
Let's go.
我们走
You know he hurting.
你知道他疼
Yeah, man. I hope he's gonna be okay.
是啊  我希望他没事
Dad!
爸
Dad, what the hell is that?
爸  那是什么
Dad! Dad!
爸  爸
Gibbons.
长臂猿
I seen a leopard tear one apart once.
我以前见过一头花豹撕碎一只长臂猿
There are leopards out here?
这里还有花豹
Leopards are all gone now. Poachers wiped 'em out.
花豹现在没了  被偷猎者猎光了
- You see that? - What? What? What?
-看到那个了吗  -什么  什么
Looked like a man walking out there.
好像有个人从那里走出来
It was just a flash, but I saw it.
一闪而过  但我看到了
- Maybe-- maybe it was a monkey. - No goddamn monkey.
-也许是只猴子  -才不是猴子
Hey, you see something?
你看到什么了吗
Clear. Clear.
没事  没事
Oh, my God.
天啊
I'm sorry about being on edge, you know. Being back here...
抱歉我一直神经兮兮的  回到这里
it is not easy.
并不轻松
It's cool.
没事
I don't like the way you did it, but I'm glad you're here.
我不喜欢你突然跑来  但你在这里我很高兴
Your daddy loves you, you know.
你要知道  你爸爸爱你
You know that, right?
你知道对吧
- You've got a funny way of showing it. - Yeah.
-你展示父爱的方式挺怪的  -嗯
But I do. I know it.
但我确实知道
I love you back.
我也爱你
Damn! Who got the bug spray? Bugs out here eating my ass up.
见鬼  杀虫喷雾在谁那  虫子要把我屁股啃掉了
Otis had it last.
之前在奥蒂斯那
Well, can you walk your
你能不能挪挪
big pigeon-toed ass over there and get it?
你的内八字屁股  到那边拿过来
What's wrong with your big lumbering ass?
你的肥屁股又怎么了
Man, you sitting right there.
兄弟  你就坐在那里
- Oh, shit. - You sitting right next to the bug spray.
-见鬼  -你就坐在杀虫喷雾边上
I gotta get up from my rock, walk over there and get it.
我得从我的石头上爬起来走过去拿
You're one lazy-ass motherfucker.
你就是个可恶的懒虫
You a Thanksgiving jive turkey giblet sorry-ass motherfucker.
你就是个喜欢夸大其词的杂碎
- Shut up. He's trying to sleep. - We up, he should be up.
-闭嘴  他还想睡呢  -我们醒了  他也该醒
Every time, you want me to get the shit.
脏活累活每次你都让我来干
You can't get up and do it your damn self.
你就是不能自己爬起来搞定
I got to get up off my damn rock and walk over there and get it.
我得从我的石头上爬起来走过去拿
You sitting right there. You get it?
你就坐在那里  你拿到了没
You see it? Big paddle ass. God damn.
你看到了吗  大肥屁股  见鬼
Hey, Paul.
保罗
Ain't this a bitch?
这他妈是想干嘛
Nigga, get up.
黑鬼  起来
- What? - Get up, nigga.
-什么  -起来  黑鬼
Why you ain't tell us, man?
你为什么不告诉我们
- What? - What?
-什么  -什么
No wonder he wanted to make all the arrangements.
难怪他想负责所有的安排
- Tien give this to you? - So, what about it?
-是田给你的吗  -那又怎样
We should all be packin', you--
我们都应该带枪的  你...
- No. - Get the gun!
-不  -拿走抢
- Come on, man! - You motherfucker!
-拜托  伙计  -你这混账
- Come on. Beat his ass down, now. - Shit.
-快  现在就扁他  -靠
You all right?
你还好吗
You a pussy-whipped motherfucker, ain't you?
你个听女人话的混蛋
Man, you don't see who she is?
你看不出她是谁吗
And that French fuck, Desroche.
那法国人德罗什也不是好东西
I don't know Desroche from Adam's house cat,
我根本不认识德罗什
but if Tiên vouched for him, that's good enough for me.
但要是田为他担保  对我来说就够了
She's a Soul Alley ho, remember that.
她就是个红灯区的妓女  别忘了
You know, Paul, you better check yourself.
保罗  你说话最好小心点
I know your mama-san's slanted pussy strung you out.
我知道你那女人的小嘴把你绑得牢牢的
She's still a fucking ho!
但她还是个妓女
Whoa, whoa, man!
兄弟
Get your motherfucking hands off me! I'll kill you!
你给我放手  我杀了你
- I'll kill that motherfucker. - Chill! Chill! Chill!
-我要杀了那狗娘养的  -冷静  别激动
Chill! What the fuck's wrong with you?
冷静  你他妈怎么回事
Breathe, man!
深呼吸
- Come on. - Give it to him.
-起来  -给他
Go ahead, give it to him.
去啊  把枪给他
Take it. I'm through with it.
拿着  我受够了
Here.
拿着
Happy?
满意了吗
Man, we're walking right on top of it.
我们就走在它上面
You said that on the last hill. Perspective's totally different.
前一座山你就这么说了  这里都变了样了
No, it's gotta be here.
不  肯定是这里
God damn! We're fucking lost!
该死的  我们迷路了
- Otis and Eddie think they slick. - What?
-奥蒂斯和埃迪觉得他们能说会道  -什么
Marching us around and around in circles
带我们一圈圈来回走
so we give up and go home.
这样我们放弃了就会回家
You come back, you collect it all for yourself, huh?
你再回来  拿了占为己有是吧
Then why'd I follow your sorry ass out here in the first place?
那我一开始干嘛还要跟着你过来
'Cause you couldn't afford the airfare, the gear, hotel.
因为你付不起机票  装备  旅馆
You needed Banker Drysdale right there.
你需要这个大金主
Shut up!
闭嘴
You and Tiên are up to something.
你跟田在谋划什么
Let me tell you something, Otis, all y'all.
我告诉你们  奥蒂斯  你们所有人
I don't need this shit. You got me? I'm here for Norm.
别搞这些  懂吗  我是为了诺姆来的
I'm here for Norm. I ain't going for no okey-doke bullshit.
我是为了诺姆来的  别给我整这些有的没的
Dope fiend double-cross, hell no. Fuck that.
嗑药  出卖  少来  妈的
Where you going? Where you going, boy?
你去哪  你要去哪
I'mma go down to the bank and make a deposit.
我去下面方便一下
- Go on, son. Handle your business. - Let me see that GPS.
-去吧  解决一下  -让我看下定位
This don't make no damn sense.
这根本说不通
Shit, man. Come on.
该死  悠着点
- Hey, Dad! Hey, guys! - What?
-爸  大伙们  -怎么了
I think I found something!
我好像找到点东西
- Gold! Gold! - Oh, shit.
-金子  金子  -妈的
Quick, bring a shovel!
快点  拿铲子来
I think I found the gold! Gold! Dad! Dad, I found it!
我好像找到金子了  金子  爸  我找到了
- I hope he really found that shit. - Gold!
-但愿他真的找到了  -金子
Where you at, son?
你在哪  儿子
Watch your step.
注意脚下
Shit, get your shovels!
快拿铲子来
Bring your shovels! Bring the shovels!
拿铲子  拿铲子
I found it! I found it! I found it!
找到了  找到了
- Watch your step over there. - Right.
-那边脚下当心  -好
Holy shit!
我去
- That's it, ain't it? - That's it.
-就是这个对吧  -就是这个
Holy...
天啊
- God damn! - Oh, man!
-妈的  -天啊
- Let me see. - Yeah, that's it.
-让我看眼  -对  就是它
Oh, shit.
妈的
Check your map. Check your map. Check your map.
看下地图  看下地图
We're in the right coordinates.
我们的方位都正确
- Yeah. Yeah. - Hey, y'all.
-对  没错  -你们看
Hallowed ground, Bloods. Holy ground.
神圣之地  誓血队  神圣之地
Yeah, that's it, right? That's it.
对  就这个对吧  就这个
Yeah, that's it.
没错  就这个
- Oh, Lord. - Yeah, that's it.
-天啊  -没错  就是这个
- Thank you, Lord. - Yeah, that's it!
-谢天谢地  -就是这个
Yeah! Yeah, it is! Yeah, it is!
没错  没错  就是这个
Yeah, it is, Bloods!
就是这个  誓血队
Let me get a picture.
让我拍张照
No! No evidence, man. No evidence.
不  不能留下证据
- Put that camera down. - My bad.
-把照相机放下  -我错了
Hold that, man.
拿好了
Yeah.
太好了
- Yeah! Yeah! - Yeah!
-太好了  -太好了
Yeah! Yeah!
太好了  太好了
Come on!
真棒
Oh, yeah. Come on, man.
太好了  快点  兄弟
- Come on, now! - Come on, man, get it.
-快点  -快挖  挖出来
Guys! Guys! I got something!
兄弟们  我找到点东西
I got something right here! Right here.
我在这边找到点东西  这边
I'm getting a hit right there.
这边探测有反应
- Right here? - Yeah.
-这边吗  -对
Okay.
好的
- Yeah, that's something there. - You in? Oh, shit!
-没错  那边是有东西  -你来吗  妈的
That's it right there.
就在那边
This the spot, right here?
就是这里了吗
- Wait, I see something here. - Watch your fingers.
-等下  我看到了什么  -手指小心
- Otis, it's right there. - Mind your hand. Look out.
-奥蒂斯  就在这  -小心手  小心了
Look out for your hands.
小心别伤着手
- Let's go. That's a lid! - I got a handle.
-再挖  那是盖子  -我看到了把手
- Shit! - What, it just come off?
-妈的  -什么  把手掉了
- Damn handle broke. - Shit. It rusted.
-该死  把手坏了  -锈掉了
Don't put the dirt back where I dug it out!
别把土拨到我才挖好的地方
- Move it out the damn way! - It's all right.
-快把它挪出来  -没事的
Here, let's just grab it. Grab it. It looks like...
我们直接拿  看起来...
Yeah. Ready? Bring it up!
好了  准备好了吗  搬起来
Shit. Wait, where is it? Where is it?
妈的  等等  金子呢  金子在哪
Come on! You gotta be kidding me.
搞什么  你开玩笑呢
Let me tip it.
让我倒一下
Fuckin' fool's gold.
他妈的金子
We are some gold-plated fools, y'all.
我们都是些只想着金子的蠢货
We're some gold-plated motherfucking fools.
我们都他妈是只想着金子的傻子
Hey, guys, guys, I got another one! I got something right here.
大伙  我又发现了  这边又有反应
Where?
哪里
- Right here. - I got it!
-这边  -我来
- Right there! - I got it! I got it! I got it!
-就那边  -我来  我来  我来
- Got that one? - Yeah.
-看好没有  -好了
All right, go.
行  挖
- I got another one! - I got it!
-我又发现一个  -我来了
- I got another one right here. - I'm coming!
-我在这里又找到一个  -我来了
- Right there. - All right.
-在那边  -好
- You good? - I'm good.
-你行吗  -行
I got a hit! Oh, shit!
我找到了  妈的
I'm getting hits everywhere!
到处都有探测反应
- Right there. Right there. - All right. Come on.
-那边  那边  -好的  快挖
- I'm getting hits all over the damn place. - Oh, shit!
-我他妈到处都能探测到东西  -妈的
All right. Put it in your pocket. Put it in your pocket.
好了  放你兜里  放你兜里
- All right, I got three right here. - I got one here.
-我这有三块  -我有一块
Keep digging. Keep digging.
接着挖  接着挖
I'm getting hits all over the mountain! All over the mountain!
满山都能探测到  到处都是
Come on, give me some.
快  来一个
Come on, baby.
碰一个
Hey, I got one here. I got one here.
这边找到一个  这边
They must've fallen in the mudslide.
肯定是泥石流冲下来了
Hey, I got something to tell y'all.
我有事要告诉你们
- What? - What?
-什么  -什么
Holy motherfucking, motherfucking, mother of gold!
妈了个蛋的  他妈的金子
- Mother of gold, motherfucker! - Get your ass over here!
-他妈的金子  该死的  -你快挪开
Why don't you start digging, roody-poo?
你怎么还不快挖
Motherfucker, I don't dig for the gold!
该死的  我才不挖金子
I find the motherfucking gold!
我他妈负责找金子
- Fuck you! - Silly-ass.
-去你的  -蠢货
- Watch your fingers. - Come on! Keep digging!
-小心手指  -快接着挖
Forty-five thousand per bar. Seventeen million all in.
每条四万五  一共一千七百万
Yeah.
没错
But I'm not leaving here without Norman.
但是我不会丢下诺曼走
You think Norman cares whether you find his remains or not?
你以为诺曼在乎你找不找得到他的遗骸吗
You remember what Norman said.
你记得诺曼的话
"That gold should go to our people."
"那金子要给我们的人民"
Whoa, what you trying to say, man?
你想说什么  兄弟
That gold should go towards black liberation.
这些金子应该给黑人解放运动
Yeah, our black liberation. You do for self.
对  解放我们这几个黑人  你是为自己
I'm talking about black reparations, man.
我说的是黑人补偿
I got mine's.
我就拿我那份
What about our people?
那我们的人民呢
What about my people?
那我呢
You do what you want with your share,
你的那份随你怎么花
and we'll each decide for ourselves.
我们的就我们自己决定
- That's what Norman said now. - Now, see? See? Otis knows.
-诺曼是那么说的  -你们看  奥蒂斯清楚
Norman wanted that gold to go towards the cause.
诺曼希望金子能贡献给大业
Yeah, that's easy for you to say, Eddie.
对  你说得轻松  埃迪
You rich. Money don't mean shit to you.
你有钱  你视金钱如粪土
- I am not rich. - Yeah, right. Whatever.
-我才没钱  -是哦  随你怎么说
- I'm not rich! - Okay.
-我真没钱  -好吧
- I'm broke, man. - How the fuck are you broke, Eddie? Huh?
-我破产了  -你怎么就破产了  埃迪
- I lost it all. - Oh, he bullshittin'.
-我身无分文  -他在扯谎
I wish I was, man.
我也希望如此
Spill it.
你说
Come on, man. Fess up.
快点说吧
Ex-wives, bad investments, back taxes,
几个前妻  投资不当  大笔税款
livin' large, drinking, being stupid.
花天酒地  人还犯蠢
You fuckin' name it, I spent money on it.
你们随便想个理由  我都花了钱
But you paid for all of this shit.
但是这一趟全是你付的钱
Yeah, yeah, I paid for all this shit
是啊  我是用一张
on a black card that's already overdrawn.
早就透支的黑卡刷的
What about all them car dealerships with your name on 'em?
那些写着你名字的汽车经销店呢
I don't own 'em.
那些不是我的
I mean, my name is good in the business and all, and...
在圈子里我的名字有利于做生意
dealers choose to use 'em, but...
经销商就喜欢用  但是
they'll pull that shit as soon as it stops working for 'em.
只要没用了  他们立刻就会改掉
I'm telling you, I ain't got a pot to piss in
我告诉你们  我都没口锅撒尿
or a window to throw it out of. And that's facts!
更没个窗户丢出去  都是真的
God damn.
该死的
Sorry, bro.
抱歉  兄弟
Can we just go find Norm?
我们能去找诺姆吗
Stormin' Norm's been waiting.
暴风诺曼一直在等
Damn.
妈的
Ain't that some doo-doo.
太惨了吧
Hey, Bloods, I got something!
誓血队  我找到东西了
Right here I got... I'm getting a big hit.
这边  有很强烈的反应
- I'm getting a big hit, right here. - Are you sure?
-反应很大  这边  -你确定吗
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It's all over,
对  没错  就这边
right in here. Right in this whole area.
就在这  就这片地方
It's a big hit. Right here. Right here.
反应很大  就在这边
Right in here, baby. Right in there.
这边  就在这边
Oh, my God! Oh, God!
天啊  天啊
That's...
那是
Shit.
妈的
It's Norm.
是诺姆
Oh, brother.
兄弟
It's Norm?
是诺姆吗
- Yeah, it's Norm. - Oh, shit.
-对  是诺姆  -妈的
Okay. Okay.
好了  好了
Holy shit. Come on.
我的天  快点
Shit. Shit.
妈的  妈的
Shit.
妈的
Hey, Norm.
诺姆
We all here, man.
我们都来了  兄弟
Otis, Melvin, Eddie.
奥蒂斯  梅尔文  埃迪
I got my son, David. Right here.
我儿子大卫也来了
Took us a little longer than we thought, but...
花的时间比预想的要久
we came back like we said we would.
但我们照约定回来了
But this time when we get on that plane, that Freedom Bird,
但这次我们会登上那架飞机  那只自由之鸟
going back to the world,
回到人世间去
you are coming with us, brother. You coming with us, brother.
你和我们一起走  一起走  兄弟
Now, both of your parents have passed,
你的双亲已经过世了
I guess you know that, but your sisters,
你应该知道了  不过你妹妹
Janet and Kim, will be waiting for us...
珍妮特和金
when we land, brother.
会在机场等我们
You goin' home, Blood.
你要回家了  手足
Come on, now.
来吧
Blessed holy God.
圣父在上
We come around your mighty throne of grace...
我们来到您伟大的恩典宝座旁
to thank you for this day.
感谢这一天的到来
We thank you for the reunion of family... and friendship...
我们感谢您让家人  朋友
and the brotherhood.
还有兄弟团聚
Continuing in prayer, Lord, we ask you for traveling grace...
我们持续祷告  主啊  祈求您保佑我们平安
and the mending of hearts.
修补我们破碎的心灵
In your son's righteous and holy name, we pray.
以您儿子正义和神圣的名义  我们向您祷告
- Amen. - Amen.
-阿门  -阿门
Damn! What is that sound?
靠  那是什么声音
Uh, cicadas.
蝉鸣
- Cicadas? - Yeah.
-蝉鸣  -嗯
They don't sound like that back home.
听起来跟家乡的不一样
We ain't home, son.
我们不在家乡  儿子
We ain't home.
不在家乡
- You all right? - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
-没事吧  -没事  没事
Hey, son, get this off of me, man.
儿子  替我把包拿下来
All right. I got it.
好了  我来
Just let it drop. Let it go.
松手  松手
Hand me my water, man.
把我的水给我
Hydrate.
补水
- Lord have mercy. - My man.
-上帝保佑  -好小子
Hey, I can manage another 30, 40 pounds.
我还能多背三四十斤
- Yeah. - That be just great, bud.
-好吗  -那太好了  伙计
My son play the pack mule, my son gets a fair share.
把我儿子当骡子使唤  就得跟我儿子平分
- It's fine, Dad. It's fine. - No, the hell it is.
-没关系的  爸  -才不是没关系
When did you turn into a grade-A, first-rate, certified,
你这个累得喘不过气的老混蛋
old, tired and crazy motherfucker?
什么时候变成疯子了
Ah, fuck you, man.
去你的
When you've been cheated in life as much as I have,
如果你这辈子像我一样吃过那么多亏
you learn to spot the sign of all them dirty rat bastards out there.
就能学会辨认那些卑鄙小人
How much you need, huh?
你想要多少
That enough? You want more?
够了吗  还要吗
Man, get that out of my fucking face.
你他妈快拿开
Get that out of my fucking face.
快他妈拿开
Do you remember?
你还记得吗
You remember what Norm said about money?
你还记得诺姆是怎么说钱的吗
I don't remember that.
不记得了
No, no, no. I am sick and tired
不  不  我受够了
of trying to get you fools to love one another.
想让你们这群蠢货彼此关爱是白费力气
Go ahead! You wanna tear each other apart, go on. Go on!
行啊  你们想自相残杀  那就动手吧
Here I thought...
我还以为
I hoped that we could be Bloods one more time.
我还希望我们能再当一次手足
But, no, that ain't gonna never happen again because of this.
但那是不可能了  都是因为这个
Traded brotherhood for this shit. Right, Paul?
用兄弟情谊换这玩意  对吧保罗
That motherfucker walks backward pigeon-toed.
那混蛋连倒着走都是内八字
"Eddie, you black as a damn crow ain't white like snow
"埃迪  天下乌鸦一般黑  你也不例外
And if you didn't know
要是你不知道
If you ain't got no dough, then you don't go
没钱就别想走
And that's for damn sure"
这是硬道理"
Yeah, well, my mama told me...
是吗  我妈妈告诉我...
that money is the root of all--
钱是万恶之...
Oh, shit!
靠
- Oh, my God! - What the fuck?
-天啊  -什么鬼
Eddie.
埃迪
- Fuck. - Oh! What?
-操  -什么
- Otis, don't move! It's a minefield! - Eddie!
-奥蒂斯  别动  这里是雷区  -埃迪
It's a minefield!
这里是雷区
Don't move, Otis.
别动  奥蒂斯
Okay, okay, okay.
好了  好了
I got you. I got you. I got you.
有我在  有我在  有我在
I got you. I got you.
有我在  有我在
- I got you. - Bloods.
-有我在  -手足啊
Jesus!
老天
- Jesus! - What?
-老天  -什么
Jesus! Dad! Dad! I think I stepped on something.
老天  爸  我觉得我踩到什么了
- Stay right there. - Motherfucker!
-别动  -混蛋
David, don't move. Don't move.
大卫  别动  别动
David!
大卫
- Everybody freeze! - Everybody okay?
-都别动  -大家没事吧
Dad, no, no! Put it down! Put it down! They can help!
爸  别  别  把枪放下  他们能帮忙
- We were just walking back to our camp. - He stepped on something.
-我们只是想回营地  -他踩到什么了
- Is it a pressure plate? - Well, if it was, he would be dead.
-是压力板吗  -如果是的话  他早就死了
Uh, maybe it's a dud. Or maybe it's not.
也许是哑雷  也许不是
- We can help you. - Look! Look! He can help.
-我们可以帮忙  -看啊  他能帮忙
Okay, come on.
好  过来
And, David... don't move.
大卫  别动
What are we gonna do about my son?
我们要怎么救我儿子
Well, all he can do is lift up his foot
他只能把脚抬起来
and pray to God it doesn't explode.
向上帝祈祷地雷不会爆炸
There's gotta be something else we can do.
肯定还有我们能做的事
Well, if there is, I don't know it.
就算有我也不知道
Fuck. Fuck! Fuck! Fuck! Fuck!
操  操  操  操  操
Jethro Bodine.
杰瑟罗·宝迪恩
- What? - Who?
-什么  -谁
Remember that big ol' hillbilly kid from Oklahoma?
还记得那个俄克拉荷马州的乡巴佬吗
He stepped on a toe popper. Remember?
他踩到了地雷  记得吗
- Yeah. Yeah. - Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
-对  对  -对对对
Okay, we're gonna spring my son...
我们要像救那个乡巴佬一样
the same way we sprung that hillbilly kid, you got me?
救我儿子  明白吗
Yeah, that'll work. That'll work.
好  那招能行  能行
Give me that rope.
把绳子给我
Where am I walking? Where am I walking?
我该往哪走  我该往哪走
Straight to me, I swept it. You're good. You're good.
向我走  我扫过雷了  没问题  没问题
Do us both a favor. Don't fucking shift your weight, okay?
帮我们个忙  千万别转移重心  好吗
Stay right where you are.
原地别动
David, I want you to take this rope.
大卫  你拿着这绳子
I want you to wrap this rope around your body. Two times.
拿绳子在你身上绕两圈
Go ahead. Twice around your body.
拿着  在身上绕两圈
Go on, like that. There you go.
就这样  好
High as you can, man. High as you can. Right.
越高越好  越高越好  对
David look at me. Where did you go to college?
大卫  看着我  你念的哪所大学
- The House. - The House.
-莫尔豪斯学院  -莫尔豪斯学院
Who went to The House?
莫尔豪斯学院的毕业生有谁
- Come on. - Edwin Moses. The class of '78.
-说啊  -埃德温·摩西  78届
- Come on. What he'd do? - Won two Olympic gold medals.
-他有什么成就  -赢得了两块奥运金牌
- Yeah. - Four hundred meter hurdles.
-对  -西百米栏
He took 13 steps between each hurdle. Everybody else took 15.
两个栏之间他跑十三步  其他人都要跑十五步
David, that man could fly.
大卫  那个人会飞
What you gonna do?
你要怎么做
- What you gonna do, David? - Fly.
-你要怎么做  大卫  -我要飞
- Like? - Fly like Moses.
-像谁一样  -像摩西一样飞
I want everybody to take a piece of this rope.
每个人都握住这根绳子
Back on up. Otis, back on up.
后退  奥蒂斯  后退
Back it on up, man. You, too, Mel. Back it on up.
后退  你也是  梅尔  后退
All right.
好
- Here, take this. - That's good, big man.
-拿着  -很好  大块头
That's good, big man! Right there. Yeah.
就这样  大块头
Fuck. Fuck.
操  操
- Get that slack! - Tighten up!
-拉紧了  -绷紧
Now, everybody...
好了  各位
you get an armful and a handful of rope.
用力握住绳子
- We good? - We good.
-准备好了吗  -好了
I hear you.
我听见了
On count of three, you pull harder than a motherfucker!
数到三  给我拼命拉
Yeah, baby.
好
You got me?
明白吗
- We got you, Blood. - Got you.
-明白  手足  -没问题
All right.
好了
One...
一
two...
二
three!
三
Come on, man.
过来
God is great.
上帝真伟大
Okay.
好了
All right. Now...
好了  现在
What the fuck?
搞什么
- Get on your knees. Get on your fucking knees. - If you get...
-都跪下  都他妈跪下  -如果你...
- Dad. - Put that damn gun down now!
-爸  -快把枪放下
We're compromised, Melvin.
我们暴露了  梅尔文
Okay, okay, okay. Just take it easy now.
好吧  好吧  先冷静一下
You know, whatever you're doing, it's none of our business.
不管你们在做什么  都与我们无关
We can just go.
我们可以直接离开
Otis, the sound of those blasts traveled, man.
奥蒂斯  爆炸声会传很远
Somebody is on their way here right now.
有人正在赶来
- We gotta get the gold and get outta here. - You serious?
-我们得拿上黄金赶紧离开  -你认真的吗
- We gotta get somebody for Eddie, Dad. - Hey, man.
-我们得找人来处理埃迪  爸  -伙计
American Embassy. Somebody.
美国大使馆之类的
- We can't tell nobody nothing. - Just slow the fuck down, man.
-我们不能告诉任何人  -先等一下好吗
We have to bury Eddie.
我们得埋葬埃迪
Are you deaf, man? Are you deaf? Are you deaf?
你是聋了吗  聋了吗  聋了吗
We gotta get out of here, Otis!
我们得赶紧离开这里  奥蒂斯
- I'm not leaving Eddie like that! - I can be helpful to you.
-我不能就这么扔下埃迪  -我可以帮你们
You can be helpful? Okay.
你可以帮我们  好
Can you bring back the dead?
你能让人起死复生吗
- Get the rope, tie 'em up. - Not doing it.
-拿绳子把他们绑起来  -我不干
Let's just talk about it.
我们先聊聊吧
Otis, you ain't giving the orders, man. I'm running shit now.
奥蒂斯  轮不到你发号施令  现在我说了算
Dad! Dad!
爸  爸
Dad nothing. Dad nothing. Dad nothing!
别叫我爸  别叫我爸  别叫我爸
Boy, I've killed far better men than you,
小子  比你更善良的人我都杀过
and I will not hesitate to plug a hole in you right now.
现在也会毫不犹疑地向你开枪
David, tie 'em up.
大卫  把他们绑起来
You want your share? Tie 'em up.
你想要平分  那就把他们绑起来
You wanna remain my son?
你想接着做我儿子
Get at it. Get at it.
那就快动手  动手
Come here, son. Come here. Come here.
过来  孩子  过来
- All right. - Give me your hand.
-好了  -把手伸出来
You had me fooled.
我被你耍了
You got something to say?
你有话要说
You say it to me. Not my son.
那就对我说  别对我儿子说
Let me tell y'all something.
我告诉你们
I'm the motherfucker.
我是老大
I'm the motherfucker. I'm the motherfucker.
我是老大  我是老大
So long, Blood.
再见  手足
Rest in power.
安息吧
Amen.
阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
-阿门  -阿门
We should give Eddie's share to his family.
我们应该把埃迪那份交给他的家人
It's the right thing to do, y'all.
那么做是对的
And David?
那大卫呢
That's my boy. He deserves a fair share.
这是我儿子  应该和他平分
Deal?
说好了
- Deal. - All right.
-说好了  -行
I can't believe I was actually...
真不敢相信我
jealous of you, back at that bar.
之前在酒吧居然嫉妒你
Yeah. You seemed so fuckin' sure of yourself.
是啊  你看起来那么自信
Should've known you're actually just a spineless fucking rat.
早该知道原来你是个没骨气的叛徒
Hedy, you can't still want this guy.
赫蒂  你不可能还对这家伙感兴趣吧
Look at him, his father's gonna kill us.
瞧瞧他  他爸会杀了我们的
Seppo, shut up.
塞波  闭嘴
Well, your father scares me more than landmines.
我觉得你爸比地雷还可怕
Shut the hell up, up there.
前面的把嘴闭上
- Yeah, over here. - Here?
-对  这里  -这里
Take us about a day, and we get to...
大概要花一天时间  接着去...
You be careful with this OxyContin shit. It can be addictive.
留神点  奥施康定可能吃上瘾
Where were we? What about right here?
我们在哪  大概这里
But I think that Vinh should--
但我觉得温应该在...
Vinh is out. He in cahoots with Charlie.
温出局了  他跟越共串通一气
Ain't that right, traitor?
不对吗  叛徒
If you don't trust me by now...
如果到现在你还不相信我
just shoot me... when you kill them.
那你杀他们的时候也打死我吧
What the hell is that?
那是什么
Night vision, baby. Night vision. Let's see what's shaking.
夜视镜  我们看看有什么动静
I need to urinate.
我要小便
- She needs to pee. - Yeah, I heard her. I'm not deaf.
-她要尿尿  -我听到了  我又不聋
Yeah, I know the Geneva Convention's off the table,
我知道让你们遵守《日内瓦公约》是没可能了
but maybe just let her take a piss.
但让她撒个尿总可以吧
Well, could you untie my hands? Please.
你能把我的手解开吗  拜托了
You gotta go, you gotta go.
人有三急
Fast, all right?
快点解决  懂吗
To the tree.
去树丛
David, don't you want the first time I unzip and remove my pants
大卫  难道你不希望我第一次在你面前脱裤子
to be under better circumstances?
是在更美好的情况下吗
Were you flirting with me the other night
那天晚上你勾搭我
because you were looking for an easy fuck
是因为你想找一夜情
or because you were actually interested in me?
还是你真的对我感兴趣
Actually, I'm interested.
我是真的感兴趣
Yeah. You left your wealthy family behind
是的  你离开富裕的家庭
to do something good, help people, kids.
来做善事  帮助别人  帮助孩子
And you're fine, too. I ain't gonna lie.
你也很漂亮  我说实话
Then let me go.
那就放了我
Give me a ten-minute head start. All I ask, please?
我只求你给我十分钟时间逃跑  拜托了
You know, I hate to cockblock. She cute, though.
我也不想坏你们的好事  不过她挺漂亮的
Mel, take her back to the tree.
梅尔  把她带回树边
You better listen to your pop, son.
你最好听你老爸的话  孩子
You're a worthless fuck. Just so you know,
你个怂逼  听好了
I was only trying to escape.
我只是想利用你逃跑
I wouldn't fuck you for all the gold in the world.
给我再多的金子  我也不会跟你上床
Just what I thought. Just what I thought.
跟我想的一样  跟我想的一样
Mel, you make sure that rope is tight.
梅尔  把绳子绑紧了
- Oh, yeah. - Hey, Dad.
-好  -爸
Okay. Okay.
好吧
- God damn! - Get the gun!
-该死的  -拿枪
- God damn! - I got the gun.
-该死的  -我拿到枪了
Drag his ass over there. Drag his ass over there.
把他拉过来  把他拉过来
- Seppo's loose! Give me the gun! - Get him.
-塞波跑了  把枪给我  -打他
I'll crack your head open!
我会打爆你的头
I knew it! I knew it!
我就知道  我就知道
Another motherfucking dope fiend double-cross.
又他妈是瘾君子出卖我们
David, you don't see what Otis is doing?
大卫  你看不破奥蒂斯的把戏吗
You're playin' into his fuckin' hands!
你正中他下怀
Your dear mother would be ashamed of you!
你妈妈会以你为耻的
Yeah, you ain't no fuckin' son of mine!
没错  你他妈才不是我儿子
You're dead to me. You hear me?
我跟你断绝关系  听到了吗
- Get the rope. - Gone! Buried!
-拿绳子  -恩断义绝
- Get the rope. - You're a fucking coward.
-拿绳子  -你是个懦夫
- Fucking disgrace! - Get the rope! Get the rope, David.
-丢死人了  -拿绳子  拿绳子  大卫
Don't get shit. You stay your ass right the fuck there.
什么都别拿  你他妈别动
You stay your ass right the fuck there!
你他妈别动
You've had quite an adventure.
你们的冒险很精彩啊
- My friend, let me help. - Oh, no.
-朋友  我来帮你  -不用
I got it, I got it. Thank you. Thank you, I got it.
我能行  谢谢  我能行
- Get this off of me. - Where's Eddie?
-帮我拿下来  -埃迪呢
Broke his ankle. We left him with food and water.
他脚踝骨折了  我们给他留了食物和水
He insisted.
他坚持要我们先走
That boy is stubborn as an old mule.
那小子跟头老骡子一样倔
- Sounds very bad. - Yeah.
-听起来很严重  -是啊
I knew you should not have gone alone.
我就知道你们不应该自己去
I have a friend in the district. He'll send a rescue group.
我有个本地朋友  他可以派救援队来
How would you like to earn more money
你想不想挣到
than you ever earned in your whole life?
这辈子都挣不来的钱
Eddie didn't break an ankle, did he?
埃迪的脚踝没骨折  对吧
No. Help me.
对  帮我一把
You kill him?
你们把他杀了
Oh, God, no.
当然没有
Minefield.
雷区
Otis!
奥蒂斯
Here come your partners.
你的搭档来了
Ain't no partners of mine.
不是我的搭档
Hedy!
赫蒂
- Hedy! - Seppo!
-赫蒂  -塞波
Seppo! Seppo!
塞波  塞波
He said you have his gold.
他说他的金子在你们手上
We trade your friend for gold.
我们用你们的朋友换金子
He ain't our friend!
他不是我们的朋友
- What? - You heard me.
-什么  -你听到了
Hedy, for God's sakes, help me.
赫蒂  求你救救我
David, you've got to help him.
大卫  你得帮帮他
Otis?
奥蒂斯
Please.
求你了
We want him alive.
你们得留他活口
- Fuck! - Fuck.
-操  -操
We can share.
我们可以平分
There's enough for everybody.
人人有份
What's he saying?
他说什么
I like you.
我喜欢你
Black Uncle Sam. We share.
黑人山姆大叔  我们分
This for you, rest for us.
这个给你  剩下的归我们
Look, man, we're Americans, all right?
伙计  我们是美国人  懂吗
You kill us or hurt him,
你杀了我们  或者伤害他
you got an international fiasco on your hands.
你就捅出国际麻烦了
We're not gonna kill anyone... yet.
我们谁都不会杀  暂时不会
You heard him.
你听到了
Nobody gets nothing. Nothing!
到时候谁都分不到  什么都分不到
Black Uncle Sam, this is belong to Vietnamese people.
黑人山姆大叔  这是越南人民的财产
We take what is ours.
我们拿走自己的东西
Hey, boy, you ain't taking what's ours.
小子  你别想拿走我们的东西
You look on that gold bar right there, it says USA, my friend.
你好好看看这些金条  上面写着美国二字
You, USA?
你  美国
Damn skippy.
该死的越南佬
- It say USA, but I don't think so. - Well, you better believe it.
-就算如此  我也不信  -你最好相信
Who the fuck are you, man?
你他妈是谁
- We? - Uh-huh. You.
-我们  -对
Vietnam officer.
越南警察
Oh, yeah? Where are your official badges?
是吗  你们的警徽呢
We don't need no stinkin' official badges.
我们不需要肮脏的警徽
Do you know Calley, brother?
你知道凯利吗  兄弟
Yeah. And first of all, you ain't my brother,
首先  你不是我兄弟
and I know California, yeah.
我知道加利福尼亚州
You imbecile.
你个弱智
It's not a state.
我说的不是州
Lt. Calley. Ever heard of My Lai?
1968年3月16日美莱村屠杀
I know all about My Lai.
我很清楚美莱村的事
And you, GI murder,
还有你们  美国兵杀人犯
killer of innocent children and babies.
杀害无辜的小孩和婴儿
There were atrocities on both sides.
双方都犯下了暴行
So why don't you go chew on some motherfucking chopsticks?
你他妈别废话了  去嚼筷子行吗
- Chill, chill, chill. - No, no, fuck him!
-冷静  冷静  -不  去他的
"Make America great again."
"让美国再次伟大"  我给你好看
- Simon! - Oh, fuck!
-西蒙  -操
Chavy! Chavy!
查维  查维
- Simon! - Stay down!
-西蒙  -趴下
Come on! Come on!
过来  过来
Chavy!
查维
Where's Norm?
诺姆去哪了
He's gone, man. KIA.
他死了  阵亡了
Đi đi mau! Let's move.
快点  我们走
- Go ahead. Go ahead! - Đi đi mau!
-去吧  去吧  -快点
Go ahead. I got this.
去吧  交给我
Okay. All right, okay.
好了  好了
- Mel! - Yeah, man.
-梅尔  -我在
- Bring a first aid kit. - Yeah.
-给我拿急救包  -好
And a satellite phone.
还有卫星电话
He's just gone!
他就这么死了
- Otis. - All right. Roll over. Roll over.
-奥蒂斯  -没事的  转过去  转过去
Turn... I know, turn over. Turn over.
转过去  我知道  转过去  子弹穿出去了
- Press this on. Press it down. - Seppo.
-按住这个  按住  -塞波
I know, boy. I know. There you go. All right.
我知道  孩子  好了
Just keep the pressure on.
用力按住
Breathe through it. Just breathe through it. Keep on going.
深呼吸  深呼吸  坚持住
Keep on. All right. Press this. Press this on.
坚持住  好  按住  按住这个
Here we go. Press it on. Press it on!
好了  按住  按住
Press it. Press it tight. All right, I know. I know. I know.
按住  用力按住  好  我知道  我知道
I know, come on. All right, you got this.
我知道  挺住  你能行的
Move your hand! I know.
手拿开  我知道
There you go. Man, it's gotta be tight.
好了  必须绑紧才行
Clean through and through.
子弹穿出去了
There you go. Hold on.
好了  等一下
Straighten up! Straighten up!
振作点  振作点
All right. All right, hold on. It's all right.
好了  等一下  没事的
How he doin'?
他怎么样
- You'll survive. You'll survive. - How's he doing, man?
-你会没事的  你会没事的  -他怎么样
That's nothing but a mosquito bite.
只不过是被蚊子叮了一下
- Don't fuck it up, man. - Come on. Come on.
-别搞砸了  -挺住  挺住
Man the hell up.
咬紧牙关
- All right. All right. All right. - Okay, look...
-好了  好了  -听着
First thing that gook's gonna do when he gets back to town,
那个越南佬回城之后做的第一件事
he gonna round up all the local muscle he can. Now look.
肯定就是召集当地所有的打手  听好
Who you callin'?
你给谁打电话
I'm calling Tiên. She can get us out of here.
我给田打电话  她可以来救我们
- What the fuck you do that for? - What the fuck...
-你他妈干什么  -搞什么
- I should shoot your crazy ass dead. - Do it.
-我就该一枪打死你这疯子  -动手啊
Ain't nothing to it but to do it, Blood.
别无他法了  手足
Don't tempt me, motherfucker.
别逼我  混蛋
What the fuck is wrong with you guys?
你们他妈是有什么毛病
Brother.
兄弟
We have very little gas left.
车里只剩一点油了
Perhaps enough gas to get to the temple ruin.
也许能开到神庙废墟
- A few miles from here. - What do we achieve by that, huh?
-离这里几公里  -去那里有什么意义
If you wanna choose to fight these men, you need some defenses.
如果你们想跟这些人打  那就需要防御
Otis, try doing the math, huh?
奥蒂斯  动动脑筋好吗  田跟越共是一伙的
Otis, that's how they knew about the gold, man.
所以他们知道金子的事
That's how this whole fucking ambush was a setup! Mel?
所以这场埋伏就是个圈套  梅尔
You know Tiên?
你认识田吗
No, I do not.
不认识
And you expect him to tell the truth.
你觉得他会说真话吗
Okay, look here. Look here, man. Okay.
好吧  听我说  听我说
We gonna cut through the jungle to a river.
我们穿过丛林走到河边
To a village, Hng Ng. Right there, Hng Ng.
沿河就能到达鸿御村  就在这里  鸿御村
Wait till nightfall. We gonna rip off a boat,
等到天黑  我们抢一艘船
and then we skirt past Tan Chau.
然后开船绕过新州县
- Hey, guys! No! - Tan Chau.
-伙计们  不行的  -新州县
We can't go there. That's 20 miles away from here.
我们过不去的  到那边要走三十多公里
So what? You scared of a little bit of exercise, fat boy? Huh?
那又怎样  你怕自己一身肥肉走不动是吗
David's leg won't handle that.
大卫的伤腿撑不住的
David ain't my problem... anymore.
我不在乎大卫的死活  再也不在乎了
Man, David is your son.
他可是你儿子
My son...
我儿子
is a backstabber.
是个背信弃义的人
Are you with us or not?
你到底上不上车
My share is my share.
我这份是属于我的
You do what you want with his share. Hear me?
他那份随你们处置  听到没
Listen, you crazy fuck!
给我听好  你这疯逼
Norman wouldn't want us to split up.
诺曼肯定不想看到我们就这么散了
That's right. He wouldn't.
没错  他肯定不想
And that's my problem. Ah. That's my problem, Otis.
但这是我的问题  是我的问题  奥蒂斯
Stormin' Norm ain't with the living. You feel me?
暴风诺曼已经死了  听懂了吗
My problem.
我的问题
Peace out!
再见
"The Lord is my shepherd! I shall not want!
"耶和华是我的牧者  我必不至缺乏
He maketh me lie down in green pastures!
祂使我躺卧在青草地上
He leadeth me beside the still waters! He restoreth my soul!
领我在可安歇的水边  祂使我的灵魂苏醒
He leadeth me in the paths of righteousness for His name's sake!
为自己的名引导我走义路
Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death,
我虽然行过死荫的幽谷
I will fear no evil, for Thou art with me.
也不怕遭害  因为你与我同在
Thy rod and Thy staff, they comfort me!"
你的杖  你的竿  都安慰我"
I can help you get it out of the country.
我可以帮你们离开越南
- All right. We'll give you a share. - How much is that?
-好  分你一份  -多少钱
Million.
一百万
We want in, too.
我们也要入伙
- You want in? - Yeah.
-你们也要  -对
All right.
好吧
Damn, Otis. Just put the gold on Craigslist.
妈的  奥蒂斯  你不如把钱扔大街上去
Mel, what am I supposed to do, huh? Eddie, Simon,
梅尔  我能怎么办  埃迪  西蒙都死了
that bullshit with Paul
保罗疯了
and the kidnapping never happened, all right?
把绑架的事忘了吧  成交吗
And what about Seppo?
那塞波的事怎么说
We all know what happened to Seppo. He stepped on a landmine.
大家都知道塞波怎么死的  他自己踩到地雷了
Hey, so real quick, just for our edification.
我有个很简单的小问题
Our share is also gonna be a million?
我们每人也能分到一百万吗
Shit!
妈的
Half.
五十万
They ain't snatching my gold. Not me. No, sir. Not this time.
他们别想动我的金子  绝对不行  想都别想
I ain't getting fucked again.
休想再耍老子
Trying to fuck me with salt in the Vaseline.
休想再用花言巧语骗老子
I dedicate this next record to brother Marvin Gaye
下面这首歌献给马文·盖伊兄弟
and to the soul brothers of the 1st Infantry Divisions.
以及大红一师136团第二营
Big Red One, 2nd Battalion, 136th Regiment.
第一步兵方阵的黑人兄弟们
Have a good day, gentlemen.
祝各位度过愉快的一天
Their mind's weak. They got no intestinal fortitude.
他们意志薄弱  缺乏勇气
Ain't as strong as Paul. No, no, sir.
不像我保罗一样坚强  差远了
Ain't got the guts Paul got. It ain't their fault.
没有我保罗这样的胆量  但这不是他们的问题
They was born weak. Otis and his ho.
他们生来如此  奥蒂斯和他的走狗们
Car thieves, guttersnipes, chain snatchers.
一群偷车贼  流浪汉  鸡鸣狗盗之辈
They ain't snatching... my gold bars.
他们可别想偷走我的金条
Not Paul. No, sir.
别想打我保罗的主意
I ain't getting fucked again.
休想再耍老子
Trying to fuck me with that salt in the Vaseline.
休想再用花言巧语骗老子
Not Paul. Not this time.
这次休想再得逞
No.
休想
Them son of bitches. Son of bitches. Son of...
这帮混账东西  混账
Turned my own son against me.
挑拨我和我儿子的关系
My own blood.
我的骨肉
God damn.
太卑鄙了
Well...
那
we gonna see who's standing in the end.
就看谁能笑到最后吧
I don't care what the VA say. VA don't know shit from Shinola.
我才不管退伍局怎么说  一帮狗屁都不懂的家伙
Worst fucking doctors in the world. Malignancy? Shit.
全世界最无能的医生  什么恶性肿瘤  胡扯
You made me malignant.
我得病都是因为你们
This fucking place here...
当年在这鬼地方
bathed me in that lymphoma Agent Orange herbicidal stew.
每天泡在致癌的除草橙剂中
Those army bastards, they scorched the earth with it.
这帮军队的混蛋  把地球都毁了
Sprayed that shit in the air and the water,
把那鬼东西洒向空气和水源
my bloodstream, my cells, my DNA, and my motherfucking soul!
侵入我的血液  细胞  DNA  还有我的灵魂
But I ain't dying...
但那玩意
from that shit.
可杀不死我
You will not...
没人能
kill Paul.
杀死我保罗
You hear me?
听见没
Hear me.
听好了
You will not kill Paul.
没人能杀死我保罗
And the US government will not take me out.
美国政府也干不掉我
I will choose
我自己决定
when...
何时何地
and how I die.
如何去死
You dig?
懂了没
You couldn't kill me then, with three tours,
三次派驻我都活下来了
you sure in the fuck can't kill me now.
现在也不可能要了我的命
Right on?
对不对
- I know that thing is throbbing like hell. - Yeah.
-你的腿肯定疼得要命吧  -是啊
Thanks.
谢了
Don't thank me. Thank your Uncle Meli-Mel.
别谢我  谢你梅尔叔叔
You OGs.
你们几个老混蛋
Hedy, he's running a fever. I think that wound is infected.
赫蒂  他发烧了  伤口可能感染了
Look after him.
照顾好他
Get off me! Get off!
滚开  滚啊
Get off!
滚
What's the issue between you and your father?
你和你父亲究竟有什么恩怨
Jacklyn.
杰奎琳
Who is she?
她是谁
My mother.
我母亲
My mom...
我妈
She had a very difficult delivery.
生我的时候难产
And she didn't survive?
没能活下来吗
My apology.
抱歉
I'm intruding. It's none of my business.
我不该问的  不关我的事
My father...
我父亲
he loved her more than me.
爱她更胜过爱我
Never let me forget that either.
他这一辈子都在提醒我这件事
He has hated me since the day I was born.
自从我出生那天  他就恨着我
All my fault.
都是我的错
I should've died instead of my mother.
当年死的如果是我就好了
Goddamn snakebite. Come on.
该死的蛇  敢咬我
Mother... Fuck you!
操他妈的
Fuck!
操
God, you're a trickster.
老天爷  你可真会捉弄人
Oh, God. You're a trickster.
你可真会捉弄人
Come to Papa.
快下来啊
Oh, f--
操
You got it, Norm. All for you, baby.
留给你了  诺姆  都是你的  宝贝
Life is a bitch!
人生何其操蛋
If I gotta go out, I gotta go out like a man, Blood.
如果我非死不可  也要像爷们一样死去  手足
Morals and ethics.
不能有违道德伦理
Sounds like Stormin' Norman.
这话听起来像暴风诺曼说的
You know, I keep hearing his voice in my head,
我脑海中总是回响着他的声音
telling me to do right, just to get it right.
叫我做正确的事  走在正道上
Stormin' had this whole living thing figured out.
暴风已经参透了生命的意义
We are not gonna die in Nam.
我们决不能死在越南
Come on, let's battle, Blood.
走吧  该上战场了  手足
Bloods.
情同手足
I was asleep.
我当时睡着了
Man, I was fast asleep, knocked out, man.
睡得很沉  像被人敲晕了一样
God poked and woke me.
上帝把我叫醒了
I said, "God... God, why you waking my black ass up?"
我问道  "上帝  为什么要唤醒我"
God said to me,
上帝对我说
"Paul, fuck them motherfuckers.
"保罗  别理那些蠢货
Keep on keeping on."
坚持下去"
I said to God, "God, do what now?"
我问上帝  "上帝  我该怎么做"
God raised His voice, didn't yell,
上帝提高了音量  但没有大喊
but put some bass in that heavenly voice, said to me,
祂神性的嗓音更低沉了些  对我说道
"Fuck them motherfuckers, Paul. They don't know shit.
"别理那些蠢货  保罗  他们一无所知
Do your thing. Show you're right."
坚持下去  证明你自己是对的"
What you doing here, bruh?
你在这干什么呢  兄弟
I've been wanting to talk to you.
我想和你谈谈
About what?
谈什么
You know.
你知道的
Go away, man.
你走吧
Please?
拜托了
No, no, come on now.
别别  别这样
Come on now. Come on now.
别这样  别这样
That I can't do, Paul.
恐怕不行  保罗
Gonna have to come clean.
得把话讲清楚
Norm! Norm!
诺姆  诺姆
There it is.
就是这样
It was an accident.
意外罢了
Ain't no thing, Blood.
没什么大不了  手足
Accident.
意外
I forgive you.
我原谅你了
You hear that?
听到没
Ain't no thing, Blood.
没什么大不了  手足
Come on now.
别在意了
Come on, Paul. Come on, Blood.
没事的  保罗  没事了  手足
I forgive you.
我原谅你了
God is love.
上帝即是爱
Love is God.
爱即是上帝
Come on. You got me now.
好了好了  我还在
You got me good. Ain't no thing.
被你打了一枪  没什么大不了
I'm sorr...
对不起
I'm sorry. I'm so sorry.
对不起  对不起
I know you, Blood.
我懂你  手足
I died for you, Blood.
我为你而死  手足
Keep digging. You're outnumbered.
继续挖  我们人多
We're always outnumbered.
我们已经习惯了以少胜多
Where's gold?
金子在哪
Stormin' Norman took it, man.
暴风诺曼拿走了
It was his.
那是属于他的
Who's Stormin' Norman?
暴风诺曼是谁
One bad black motherfucker.
一个牛逼黑鬼
Where's all the GI?
那些美国兵在哪
No, I will never tell.
我是不会说的
See, we're Bloods.
明白吗  我们情同手足
We got a bond.
我们有羁绊
We fought... in a immoral war that wasn't ours,
我们在一场不属于我们的不义战争中拼命
for rights... for rights we didn't have.
为我们未曾拥有的权利而战
They're my brothers.
他们是我的兄弟
You killed my brother.
你杀了我的兄弟
I did.
没错
♪ Don't go and talk about my father ♪
♪ 不要妄议我的父亲 ♪
♪ God is my friend, Jesus is my friend ♪
♪ 上帝是我的朋友  耶稣是我的朋友 ♪
♪ He made this world for us to live in ♪
♪ 祂创造了我们居住的世界 ♪
♪ And gave us everything ♪
♪ 赋予了我们一切 ♪
♪ All He asks of us ♪
♪ 而祂只求 ♪
♪ Is we give each other love ♪
♪ 我们关爱彼此 ♪
- My brother, Marvin. - You're drunk.
-我的兄弟  马文  -你喝多了
- I ain't never been more sober in my life. - Dig!
-我这辈子从没如此清醒  -快挖
Okay, it's deep enough, man.
好了  这够深了  哥们
Okay... dig.
好吧  挖
♪ Don't go and talk about my father ♪
♪ 不要妄议我的父亲 ♪
Faster!
快点
♪ God ♪
♪ 上帝 ♪
- Faster! - ♪ Is my friend Jesus is my friend ♪
-快点  -♪ 是我的朋友  耶稣是我的朋友 ♪
- Faster! - ♪ He loves us ♪
-再快点  -♪ 祂爱我们 ♪
- Faster. - ♪ Whether or not we know it ♪
-再快点  -♪ 无论我们是否知晓 ♪
♪ And He'll forgive us all our sins ♪
♪ 祂会宽恕我们的一切罪过 ♪
You all right up there?
你在上面怎么样
- Keep your eyes open. - On it.
-保持警惕  -没问题
Kool and the Gang.
库尔与黑帮
After you've been in a war,
经历过战争
you understand it really never ends.
就会知道战争永无休止
Whether it's in your mind or in reality.
不管是在你心中还是在现实中
There are just degrees.
只是程度不同罢了
Tell me about it.
确实如此
If I happen to die, send my share here.
如果我遭遇了不幸  把我那份送到这里去
One of you two should have this.
你们中得有人拿着这个
No. I don't want it.
不  我不想要
I ain't fired a gun in my life.
我这辈子都没开过枪
I shoot, I'd probably miss by a mile, especially with my leg.
拖着这条伤腿  更没法瞄准了
My father? You seen him?
我爸  你见到他了吗
My hunch is Desroche is with him.
我猜德罗什找到他了
- Who? - One of your countrymen.
-谁  -你的一个同乡
He set up our deal, probably gave us the old flimflam.
他安排了我们的交易  大概就是他坑了我们
Perhaps I could appeal to him.
也许我可以说通他
Worth a try.
值得一试
Are you ready for this?
你准备好了吗
Blood, this ain't my first time in Nam.
手足  这不是我第一次来越南了
Well, if we live, you'll teach me that.
如果我们活下来了  你得教我那个
We're all gonna live.
我们都会活下来的
And maybe someday if I come to Paris,
如果哪天我去了巴黎
you can show me the "Champs-Eleesees."
你可以带我去看看"乡谢里谢"
The what?
什么
You know, the "Champs-Eleesees"? That big thing y'all got.
"乡谢里谢"  你们那里的大家伙
The Champs-élysées.
香榭丽舍大道
- Bet? - Bet.
-说定了  -说定了
Remember the plan.
记住计划
Yes, sir.
是  先生
Who is your pretty companion?
你身边的美女是哪位
What'd he just say?
他说什么了
That the green is more important than black.
他说绿钞票比黑皮肤更重要
He asks for Norman's share.
他想要诺曼的那份
I don't know.
我不知道
Norman is pretty particular about what he shares.
诺曼对于他所得多少非常挑剔
- May I ask you a question? - Yes.
-我能问你个问题吗  -可以
Was Tiên in on all this?
田有参与这事吗
Tiên is a very smart woman,
田是个很聪明的女人
but she doesn't have the appetite for a venture like this.
但她对于这种风险不感兴趣
She knows nothing about this.
她对此毫不知情
She is as innocent as you are ignorant.
她很清白  正如你愚昧无知
Well, take the gold and...
好吧  拿上金子...
leave in peace.
还这里一个安宁吧
Go with God.
遵从上帝旨意
We just want what we came for.
我们只要自己应得的东西
Good.
很好
You bastards!
混蛋
Go, go, go!
快走  快走
- I can't feel a thing. - Fuck.
-我没知觉了  -妈的
Straight through. Through and through.
撑住  撑住
- You'll survive, buddy. - Be safe.
-你会没事的  哥们  -小心
Grenade!
手榴弹
No!
不
Your Bloods are all dead.
你们誓血队都死光了
There is no one left.
无一幸免
Where is the gold?
金子在哪
Five Bloods don't die,
誓血五人组不会消亡
we multiply.
我们生生不息
Allow me.
我让你灭亡
Madness! Madness!
疯狂啊  疯狂啊
Godfather, you'll be all right.
教父  你会没事的
Dear David.
亲爱的大卫
Son...
儿子
if you're reading this,
如果你读到了这封信
you know I've met my maker.
你就知道我已经不在了
I gave this letter to...
陈兴道
my main man,
交给了我的好兄弟
your godfather, Otis,
你的教父  奥蒂斯
when we landed back in Nam.
胡志明市战争犯罪博物馆
I came back to confront the demons
我回到越南  直面纠缠着我
that haunted me and tortured you.
并且折磨着你的业障
I made you feel like you weren't loved.
我让你感受不到我的爱
Our brother Stormin' Norman always commanded us Bloods,
我们的兄弟暴风诺曼总是命令我们手足
love one another.
关爱彼此
In that way, I failed you, man.
从这点来讲  我辜负了你
All I can say to you is...
我只能对你说...
I'm sorry I put you through holy hell.
很抱歉我让你受了那么多苦
Believe me...
相信我
This just came.
这个刚刚寄到
it wasn't your fault.
这不是你的错
There are things about me
有些关于我的事
that you will never know or understand, David.
是你永远无法知晓或理解的  大卫
I wish I could turn back the hands of time...
我希望我能扭转时间之手...
I can't.
但我不能
Nobody can.
没人做得到
- Mic check! - Mic check!
-试麦  -试麦
I got something I gotta share with y'all.
我有事要和大家分享
We just received a check from our soldier Eddie
我们刚刚收到了我们的战士埃迪寄来的
for two million dollars!
两百万美元的支票
- Mic check! - Mic check!
-试麦  -试麦
When I say "black lives," y'all say "matter!"
我说"黑人命"  你们说"也是命"
- Black lives! - Matter!
-黑人命  -也是命
- Black lives matter! - Black lives matter!
-黑人命也是命  -黑人命也是命
Black lives matter! Black lives matter!
黑人命也是命  黑人命也是命
LAMB
塞伯·哈韦林基金会 LAMB 用爱清除地雷炸弹
Thank you.
谢谢大家
Thank you, everyone being here on this sad but beautiful day.
谢谢大家在这悲伤但美丽的一天里相聚
And I'm happy to tell you that this three million dollar gift
我很高兴地宣布  这笔三百万美元的捐款
is donated in the name of my late colleague,
将以我已故同事的名义捐赠
Seppo Havelin,
塞伯·哈韦林
and will work toward removing mines and bombs,
捐款将用于清除地雷和炸弹
and also restoring the lives of victims all over the world.
以及重建世界各地受害者的生活
Left.
左
But to eternity and back,
不过无论如何
your dear mother, Jackie, and I...
你亲爱的母亲  杰姬  还有我
will love you always.
会一直爱你
You best believe I will love you always, son.
你要相信我永远爱你  儿子
Your father.
你的父亲
Your dad.
你的爸爸
Otis.
奥蒂斯
I couldn't go back home without seeing you both before I left.
我动身回家之前必须见见你们俩
I miss you. And I love you so...
我想你  我好爱你
And I love you.
我也爱你
To save the soul of America.
马丁·路德·金 河边教堂 纽约州  纽约市 1967年4月4日
We were convinced that we could not limit our vision
我们坚信不能将视野局限在
to certain rights for black people...
为黑人争取某些权利上
but instead affirmed the conviction
而是要认定一个事实
that America would never be free or saved from itself
在时至今日仍然深陷囹圄的黑人奴隶的后代子孙
until the descendants of its slaves
完全从枷锁中解脱出来之前
were loosed completely from the shackles they still wear.
美国永远无法真正自由  也永远无法完成自我救赎
In a way, we were agreeing with Langston Hughes,
某种程度上  我们赞同兰斯顿·休斯所说
that black bard of Harlem,
哈林区的那位黑人吟游诗人
who had written earlier,
他之前曾写过
"Oh, yes I say it plain
"没错  我说得如此直白
America never was America to me
美国于我而言从不是美国
And yet I swear this oath America will be!"
但我发誓有朝一日美国会成为美国"
Be safe.
保重
Shit!
妈的
Cut!
停